<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Saints testimony finishing through sufferings: or, The proceedings of the court against the servants of Jesus, who were called before them to be tryed at the late assizes (or sessions) held in Banbury in the county of Oxon, the 26 day of the seventh moneth, 1655. Also a relation of Margret Vivers, going to the steeple-house in Banbury, after the assize (or sessions) as aforesaid: and a testimony against false prophets, and false doctrine; ... And the manner of Richard Farnsworth imprisonment at Banbury, with a short examination and answer. And the cause of his detainment. Also, a warning from the spirit of the Lord (in his hand-maid Anne Audland) to the persecuting priest and people, &amp;c. And a letter of Robert Rich to the magistrates of Banbury, ... Likewise a letter of Tho. Curtis to the professed minister called Samuel VVells in Banbury. And a certificate wherein is manifested the diligence that was used to know the causes of the prisoners commitments ... (Anne Audland, Iane VVaugh, Sarah Tims, and Nathaniel VVeston) as wel as Robert Rich, ... With a paper relating the sufferings of the innocent.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E857_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203441</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863395</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115594</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115594)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E857[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Saints testimony finishing through sufferings: or, The proceedings of the court against the servants of Jesus, who were called before them to be tryed at the late assizes (or sessions) held in Banbury in the county of Oxon, the 26 day of the seventh moneth, 1655. Also a relation of Margret Vivers, going to the steeple-house in Banbury, after the assize (or sessions) as aforesaid: and a testimony against false prophets, and false doctrine; ... And the manner of Richard Farnsworth imprisonment at Banbury, with a short examination and answer. And the cause of his detainment. Also, a warning from the spirit of the Lord (in his hand-maid Anne Audland) to the persecuting priest and people, &amp;c. And a letter of Robert Rich to the magistrates of Banbury, ... Likewise a letter of Tho. Curtis to the professed minister called Samuel VVells in Banbury. And a certificate wherein is manifested the diligence that was used to know the causes of the prisoners commitments ... (Anne Audland, Iane VVaugh, Sarah Tims, and Nathaniel VVeston) as wel as Robert Rich, ... With a paper relating the sufferings of the innocent.</title>
                  <author>Vivers, Margaret.</author>
                  <author>Audland, Anne, 1626 or 7-1705.</author>
                  <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
                  <author>Curtis, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-Spread-Eagle, neer the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes "A true declaration of the suffering of the innocent, who is hated and persecuted without a cause" by Anne Audland (D3v-E3r), previously published separately.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 3d Nov. 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>R. F. --  (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115594:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE SAINTS TESTIMONY Finiſhing through SVFFERINGS: <hi>OR,</hi> The Proceedings of the Court againſt the Servants of Jeſus, who were called before them to be tryed at the late Aſſizes (or Seſſions) held in <hi>Banbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxon,</hi> the 26 day of the ſeventh Moneth, 1655.</p>
                  <p>Alſo a Relation of <hi>Margret Vivers,</hi> going to the Steeple-houſe in <hi>Banbury,</hi> after the Aſſize (or Seſſions) as aforeſaid: And a Teſtimony againſt Falſe Prophets, and falſe Doctrine; with an Anſwer to the Objection about the woman forbidden to ſpeak in the Church: And ſome paſſages about the Lords former ſending of his Servants and Meſſengers. And who are no Jeſuits, Fugitives, nor Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds. And the manner of <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> impriſonment at <hi>Banbury,</hi> with a ſhort Examination and Anſwer. And the cauſe of his detainment.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, A Warning from the Spirit of the Lord (in his hand-maid <hi>Anne Audland</hi>) to the perſecuting Prieſt and people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a Letter of <hi>Robert Rich</hi> to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Banbury,</hi> and to <hi>Iohn Griffith,</hi> Deputy Recorder, who ſate Iudge in their Court, at the Aſſize (or Seſſion) as aforeſaid. Likewiſe a Letter of <hi>Tho. Curtis</hi> to the profeſſed Miniſter called <hi>Samuel VVells</hi> in <hi>Banbury.</hi> And a Certificate wherein is manifeſted the diligence that was uſed to know the cauſes of the priſoners com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitments that were called to a trial at <hi>Banbury,</hi> (<hi>Anne Audland, Iane VVaugh, Sarah Tims,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel VVeſton</hi>) as wel as <hi>Robert Rich,</hi> who was that day committed out of the Court to priſon in <hi>Banbury.</hi> With a Paper relating the ſufferings of the Innocent.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rev. 12.13. &amp; 17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And when the <hi>Dragon</hi> ſaw that he was cast unto the Earth, he perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the woman which brought forth the Manchild: and the <hi>Dragon</hi> was wrath with the woman, and went to make war with the remnant of her ſeed, which keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and have the teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black-Spread-Eagle, neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1655.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115594:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115594:2"/>
                  <head>THE Saints Teſtimony Finiſhing through SUFFERINGS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here being a General Seſſions (and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Goal-Delivery) holden at the Town and Burrough of <hi>Banbury,</hi> the fourth day of the week, being the ſix and twentieth day of the ſeventh moneth, 1655. and to many known, that ſeveral of the Servants of the Living God were there impriſoned, whom the world in ſcorn calls quakers; ſo many friends to them and the truth of God, were moved out of Briſtol, Gloceſterſhire, Barkſhire, and other parts of the Nation, to come and viſit them, and to uſe their endeavors that juſtice and equity might be done them; at the beginning of the Seſſions we were there, and heard the Charge given, and was preſent the whole time all our friends were tryed, and obſerved as followeth.</p>
                  <p>After awhile, one <hi>Thomas Colle</hi> was called into the Court, (who bore ſom office in the Town,) when he appeared, it was obſerved great rage againſt him role, yet little was ſaid to him, but that he was unmannerly in that he kept on his hat; and they asked him, if he knew where he was, or before whom, and ſaid that he affronted the Court, and words to that purpoſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the man uttered not one uncivil word; whereupon the Deputy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115594:3"/>called <hi>Iohn Griffith,</hi> who ſate Judge in the Court, fined him to pay five pounds, &amp; condemned him to priſon til he ſhould pay the ſame, &amp; he was fined forty ſhillings more for neglect of his office, as they ſaid, and becauſe be refuſed to pay the money, was ſent to priſon accordingly, as they had commanded. This hard ſentence being thus paſſed, was a great burthen to them who loved Righteouſneſs, and expected equity; And clearly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſaid <hi>Thomas Cole</hi> for conſcience ſake could not reſpect any ones perſon, he being enlightned with the light of Chriſt Jeſus, which reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth no mans perſon, and in obedience to him and the Apoſtle who was guided by the ſame ſpirit of Light, who ſaith; <hi>My brethren, have not the faith of our Ieſus Chriſt, the Lord of glory, with reſpect of perſons, for if ye reſpect perſon yee commit ſin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iames</hi> 1.9.</note> 
                     <hi>and are convinced of the Law as Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</hi> After that the ſaid <hi>Thomas Cole</hi> was ſent to the priſon as aforeſaid, one <hi>Robert Rich</hi> (ſtanding not far from the place where the Judge ſate) who is a friend to all that love righteouſneſs, was made a witneſs for the juſt GOD againſt all injuſtice and deceit, he ſeeing and hearing the ſaid Judge, and ſome others that ſate neer him on the Bench, earneſtly inviting two men (that was in the Court with their hats off) whole names (as was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards informed, were two Prieſts, <hi>viz.</hi> Prieſt <hi>Smart,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Iones,</hi>) to the tranſgreſſion of the ſame thing, for which a little before they had fined and ſent to priſon <hi>Thomas Cole,</hi> namely to the putting and keeping on their hats; the aforeſaid <hi>Robert Rich</hi> taking notice of their partiality, and unjuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings herein, and to ſee the Law of God not regarded by them, but threw behind their backs, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not respect the perſon of the poor, nor honor the perſon of the mighty, but in righteouſneſs ſhalt thou judge thy Neighbor;</hi> was moved of the Lord to ſpeak after this manner: Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus who reſpecteth not the perſon of any man, and judgeth righteouſly, will give unto every one of you according to your deeds, and they that judge ought to judge righteous Judgement, without reſpect of perſons; ſome ſmall enmity aroſe againſt him, and one ſitting on the Bench asked what buſineſs he had in the Town, who anſwered, he came to viſit ſome friends; they asked his name, and where he lived, to both which he gave a meek &amp; a juſt anſwer; preſently after this the court a journed til the afternoon.</p>
                  <p>In the afternoon friends came again to the Court, where the Magiſtrates was ſet, &amp; within a ſhort time ſhe (who is called <hi>Anne Audland</hi>) was called to the Bar, &amp; there in the Court an inditement was read againſt her, charging her with blaſphemy, &amp; on they did proceed to tryal, called a Jury &amp; brought in their witneſſes, which differed one from another, and was in confuſion, though they pretended to bear witneſs to one and the ſame thing, but falſly was the accuſed, &amp; there did declare againſt, &amp; deny in the preſence of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, thoſe things charged upon her: ſo he that ſate as Judg in the court, ſpoke to the Jury, that all which was proved could not be found, or would not prove blaſphemy, &amp; words to them to that purpoſe; ſo they went aſide to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, &amp; being together, where by the Law they ought to have bin kept alone, til they were agreed upon their verdict, and being together could not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115594:3"/>find the bil, for ſome of the Jury ſaid, why ſhould we find this bil, ſeeing we have not evidence to prove it? or words to that purpoſe, &amp; ſo threw it by; but one of them that ſate on the Bench that ſame day, &amp; is called a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> came in to the Jury, when they were together, to corrupt and inſtigate them, as ſome of the Jury hath confeſſed, which was contrary to the known Law of the Nation in ſuch caſes provided, &amp; contrary to truth and equity, which is a greater crime and breach of the Law, then thoſe things which many of the ſervants of Jeſus are impriſoned for. And after awhile the Jury came into the court, &amp; was asked if they were agreed, to which they ſaid they were; &amp; gave in their verdict for the <hi>Protector,</hi> but they ſaid they found not blaſphemy, it was then demanded what was found? to which they ſaid miſdemeanor; then ſhe deſired to know what ſhe was accuſed of, for they read then bil, &amp; called their witneſſes for blaſphemy, but blaſphemy was not found; then they ſaid they found miſdemeanor againſt her, the asked in what? they ſaid in calling the <hi>Miniſter</hi> a falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> but ſhe denyed that ſhe did, as they ſaid, although its no <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> to call them <hi>falſe prophets</hi> who are <hi>falſe prophets,</hi> which doth not abide in the <hi>doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, and their <hi>miniſter</hi> being then on the <hi>bench</hi> in the Court, was asked what he had to accuſe her of; he anſwered, <hi>he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred his cauſe to God, and ſaid he deſired ſhe might have what favour the Law would afford;</hi> yet for all this, though the Bil was not found, and though their as they call him, there preſent, did not <hi>accuſe</hi> her of any thing, they committed her to Priſon again, who had been there <hi>priſoner</hi> nine months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and faſly accuſed at her firſt commitment, for no other thing did ſhe ſpeak but the truth, according to plain Scripture, a true Relation of which is publiſhed and declared in a printed paper, being intituled, <hi>A true Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſuffering of the Innocent, who is hated and perſecuted without a cauſe,</hi> which is made manifeſt dayly, <hi>for which the righteous Iudge of all the world will deal righteously, and call you to an account, and weigh you in an equal bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and meaſure you in a juſt meaſure, and from the hand of the Lord muſt you receive a reward according to your deeds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After that, then there was one <hi>Iane VVaugh</hi> called to the Barre, who had been impriſoned about ſixteen Weeks before, in the Town of <hi>Banbury,</hi> who at firſt coming thither, was in obedience to the Lord, to declare his truth, and witneſs againſt deceit, for which ſhe were beaten, and abuſed, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and impriſoned, and evilly entreated in the ſaid <hi>Banbury,</hi> as the ſervants of the Lord in former ages (as wel as this) were, by ſuch an evill genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſeed of evil doers, as they are, whoſe fruits makes them manifeſt, to be guided by the ſame ſpirit (though under a refined ſubtilty) that other perſecutors of the innocent, ſpoken of in Scripture were. The ſaid <hi>Iane VVaugh,</hi> as foreſaid, who had been a witneſs to the truth of God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deceit of the world; and after ſhe had been ſore abuſed in the ſaid <hi>Banbury,</hi> perſecuted, impriſoned, and put forth of the Town, for witneſſing the truth againſt deceit; and after a certain time, being moved by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord to come into <hi>Banbury</hi> again, and being with a friend getting him to write a Letter for her; the Magiſtrates hearing of her being there, ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115594:4"/>for her to come before them; <hi>Iohn Auſtine</hi> who was then Mayor, cauſed the Oath of Abjuration to be tendred unto her, and becauſe in obedience to the commands of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> ſhe refuſed to ſwear, being faithfull to him, abiding in his Doctrine; and although ſhe ſo did in obedience to his Command, out of love to him and his truth; and there in their court, when the ſaid Oath was tendred, ſhe utterly denyed all things contained in that Oath, and Witneſſed againſt all Popery, and Popiſh, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall Opinions whatſoever; yet the was then (notwithſtanding all that) committed to Priſon, where the remained (though the breach of any Law were not laid to her charge) til the Generall Seſſions, Aſſize, or pretended Goal-Delivery, when and where ſhe was called to the Bar, as aboveſaid, and appearing there that day, where no Accuſation and witneſs came in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, nor any breach of the Law or miſ-demeanor laid to her charge; but notwithſtanding, ſhe was asked to put in ſureties for her good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; then ſhe asked them on the bench, what Law ſhe had broken, and would have had them to have convinced her of a tranſgreſſion, by making known to her the breach of ſome Law, the which they refuſed; but ſhe could get no other anſwer, but that if ſhe would not give in ſureties, ſhe muſt to priſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which was done accordingly; now let all the wiſe in heart, that truly fear God, conſider whether theſe proceedings againſt the innocent be either legall or juſt; and if they do not exceed the proceedings of heathen Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, who ſate Judges in tryals againſt the Chriſtians and ſervants of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in former ages, as in the Scriptures are left upon Record.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, and ſee the actings of the perſecuting Jews, who had the form, but wanted the power, and ſo out of a blind zeal perſecuted the Servants of Ieſus, who were in the power and life of truth, and they were ſore moved and offended at the Servants of Ieſus, and exceeding mad againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> who was preſſed in Spirit (being in <hi>Macedonia</hi>) to teſtifie to the Iews that Ieſus was Chriſt; and when they apoſted themſelves and blaſphemed, he ſhoke his Rayment, and ſaid unto them, your blood be upon your own heads, and having cleared his conſcience to them, he departed, and went to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and ſo entred into a certain mans houſe that worſhipped God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moved of the Lord, he ſpoke and was not afraid, the Lord being with him, and having much people in that place, where he continued a year and ſix months, teaching the word of God among them; and the Iews which made inſurrection againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> when they brought him before the Deputy of <hi>Achaia</hi> for teaching the word of the Lord, which their dark minds (who lived in Envie and Malice againſt the truth) could not receive: And now obſerve the actings of the Deputy of <hi>Achaia</hi> (who though he might be accounted a heathen or an Antichriſtian) whoſe proceedings in that caſe might preach or teach wiſdome to ſome who profeſs themſelves to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates; for when <hi>Gallio</hi> was the Deputy of <hi>Achaia</hi> (as <hi>Iohn Griffith</hi> Deputy-Recorder was Iudge in the Court, at the aſſize or ſeſsions in <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury;</hi> before whoſe judgement ſeat the ſervants of Ieſus was brought, by ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115594:4"/>as had made inſurrection againſt them in their Market, Steeplehouſe, and Steeplehouſe-yard, in nature, like the envious perſecutors of the Servants of Jeſus: For, the Iews made inſurrection againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and brought him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Gallio</hi> to the Iudgement Seat, and laid down their accuſations againſt him, (according to Law, there and then accuſing him to the Deputy, who ſate as Judge, ſaying, in their accuſation, this fellow (to wit, <hi>Paul</hi>) perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth men to worſhip God contrary to the Law; and when <hi>Paul</hi> (the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) was about to open his mouth to anſwer (againſt that accuſation and) for himſelf (the Deputy of <hi>Achaia</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> was brought before, to wit) <hi>Gallio,</hi> anſwered and ſaid unto the Iews (very wiſely in the Priſoners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, who it is likely in his conſcience was convinced of their envie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt him, he ſaid to the accuſers) if it were a matter of wrong or wicked lewdneſs, O ye Iews (being troubled to ſee their unjuſt accuſations, and unreaſonable actings) reaſon would (ſaith he) that I ſhould bear with you, but if it be a queſtion of words or names; and of your Law, look ye to it, for I wil be no Iudge in ſuch matter, and he drove them from the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.12, 13, 14, 15, 16,</p>
                  <p>So where wicked lewdneſs or a matter of wrong is committed, reaſon doth require to hear it; and reaſonable men to determine or judge according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; that are to judge in that caſe, and to hear the accuſed as wel as the accuſers, that Juſtice may be Miniſtred according to the offences, but if it be a queſtion of words, or names; or telling hireling Prieſts or falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of their deceits and falſe worſhips, who profeſs themſelves to be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt and are not, let them either plead their cauſe from the Scriptures, if they can, to procure their practiſe to be according thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or elſe let them cover their faces for ſhame.</p>
                  <p>After <hi>Paul,</hi> who was brought before <hi>Gallioes</hi> Judgement ſeat, had taken leave of the brethren, (being at liberty) he went thence into <hi>Syria,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and there entred into the Synagogue, and reaſoned with the <hi>Iews,</hi> and went from <hi>Epheſus</hi> unto <hi>Ceſaria,</hi> and when he had ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Church, he went down to <hi>Antioch,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 18.18. to the 24.</note> and ſpent ſome time before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted (and having his freedom) departing from <hi>Antioch,</hi> he went over all the Countrey of <hi>Galathia,</hi> and <hi>Phrygia,</hi> ſtrengthning the Diſciples (and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he thus wandred or went through the Countries, yet were he neither Ieſuit, Fugitive, nor Vagabond) and paſſing through the upper Coſts, came to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and there finding Diſciples, he layed his hands on them, and were ſtrengthned by him, and he went into the Synagogue, and there boldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the things which concerned the Kingdom of God, where ſome belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as others who believed not were hardned, and ſpake evil of the truth, (as they do now.) And there were ſeven Sons of one of the Iews, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Vagabonds Iews, and chief of the Prieſts, who were hypocrites, that i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitated or counterfeited the way of God, and had a juſt recompense for their reward, ſo that they fled out of the houſe naked and wounded, ſo there aroſe no ſmall ſtir about that way, for they that were in the falſe worſhip
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115594:5"/>made a great uproar, but the Town Clerk appeared the people, and did not impute it to <hi>Paul,</hi> but ſaid to the rude multitude and falſe worſhippers, that they ought to be quiet, and to do nothing raſhly, and told them that they were in danger to be called in queſtion for that dayes uproar; and did not lay it to <hi>Pauls</hi> charge, that he was the cauſe of this their Tumult and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, although he had declared againſt their deceit and falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and after the uproar was ceaſed, <hi>Paul</hi> called the Diſciples unto him, and imbraced them, and was not at that time committed to Priſon, but departed from thence and went into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and when he had gone over thoſe parts, and had given them exhortation, he came into <hi>Greece,</hi> and paſſing through ſeverall places and countries, ſtrengthning the <hi>Diſciples, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Kingdome of God, freely declaring the counſell of God, coveting no mans ſilver nor Gold,</hi> and as he finiſhed his courſe, the <hi>Iews</hi> (and falſe worſhippers) which were of <hi>Aſia,</hi> when they ſaw him in the Temple (who had not the command there, but the chief Prieſts and perſecuting Iews, their party, who) crying out and ſaid, <hi>Men of Iſrael help, this is the man that teacheth all men every where, againſt the people and the law and this place; (meaning the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,)</hi> and all the City was moved, and the people ran together, and they took <hi>Paul</hi> and drew him out of the Temple, (as they now do out of their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Idol-Temples,</hi> ſuch as are <hi>witneſſes</hi> againſt <hi>deceit</hi>) and forth with their doors was ſhut,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 21.27, 28, 30, 31, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> and as they went about to kill him (their <hi>envy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great, and their <hi>rage</hi> high) <hi>Liſſius</hi> the <hi>chiefe Captain</hi> hearing that the whole City were in an uproar, and finding the <hi>Iews</hi> going about to kil <hi>Paul,</hi> they ſeeing the Captain and ſouldiery coming, left beating of him, ſo the <hi>chiefe Captain</hi> took <hi>Paul</hi> out of their hands, demanding who he was, and what he had done, and the <hi>multitude</hi> being <hi>confuſed,</hi> ſome crying one thing, and ſome another; and not knowing the certainty, he commanded him to be carryed into the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> and on the <hi>Staires</hi> he was preſerved, and born of the <hi>Souldiery</hi> from the <hi>violence</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> who tumultuouſly followed after him, crying, <hi>away with him;</hi> and when he was on the <hi>Staires,</hi> the Captain gave <hi>Paul</hi> Lycence &amp; liberty to clear his <hi>conſcience</hi> to them, which, when he had done the <hi>Zealous falſeworſhippers,</hi> and <hi>antichriſtians,</hi> lifted uptheir voyces and cryed, <hi>away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, it is not fit that he ſhould live, Act.</hi> 21.40. &amp; the 22.1. to the 23. ver. And their <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> being great, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had judged him not fit to live, and had not the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> preſerved him, they had taken away his life, when they cryed out againſt him, caſt off their Cloathes, and threw duſt in the ayre. Then the Captain commanded him to be brought into the Caſtle, to be examined, that he might know wherefore they cryed ſo againſt him; and the Captain (through mis-infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) cauſed him to be ſcourged and bound with thongs, contrary to the Law of the <hi>Romans,</hi> being un-condemned, who after he knew that <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>Roman,</hi> he was afraid, becauſe he had acted contrary to the Law: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he knew the certainty wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> was accuſed of the Jews, he dealt juſtly, and looſed him from his bonds, and commanded the chief Prieſt and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115594:5"/>all their counſel (his accuſers) to appear, and brought <hi>Paul</hi> down, and ſet him before them, giving him liberty to ſpeak for himſelf; and after he had ſpoken for himſelf, and the truth being cleared, there was a Diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people, and many received it, though it were by others rejected, who continued in their perſecution; and the Captain fearing leſt they ſhould bave pulled him in pieces, preſerved him out of their hands, and after that the chief Captain heard that the chief prieſts and jews had conſpired againſt <hi>Paul</hi> to take away his life, and fourty of them had bound themſelves under a great curſe, that they would neither eat nor drink until they had killed him; but the Governour preſerved him out of their cruell hands, and ſent <hi>Paul</hi> away by night unto <hi>Ceſaria,</hi> (providing with him neceſſaries meet for that journey, and ſo ſent him ſafely to <hi>Faelex</hi> the Governour, with an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> ſhewing the cauſe wherefore he was committed, or taken into his cuſtody, with the <hi>Iews accuſations</hi> laid to his <hi>charge,</hi> or ſpoak of the Jews that accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, who ſought to take away his <hi>life,</hi> which he underſtood to be worthy neither of death, nor of bonds; and therefore he gave <hi>commandment</hi> to his <hi>accuſers</hi> to appear befor <hi>Foelex,</hi> to ſay what they had againſt him. And when the <hi>Souldiers</hi> came to <hi>Ceſaria,</hi> they delivered the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Foelex</hi> the <hi>Gove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> and preſented <hi>Paul</hi> alſo before him, who when he had read the <hi>Epistle,</hi> and asked of what <hi>Province</hi> he was, underſtanding he was of <hi>Celiſcia,</hi> dealt nobly with him, ſaying, <hi>He would hear him when his accuſers was come:</hi> And after they came with a certain <hi>Oritor,</hi> who informed the <hi>Governour</hi> againſt <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Priſoner,</hi> and begun to accuſe him, laying many <hi>falſe accuſations</hi> againſt him as at this time they do againſt the ſervants of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who abide in his Doctrine as <hi>Paul</hi> did, whom they in their <hi>accuſation</hi> ſaid he was ſound a <hi>peſtilent fellow,</hi> and a mover of <hi>ſedition</hi> amongſt all the <hi>Iews</hi> throughout the world, and a <hi>Ring-leader</hi> of the <hi>Sect</hi> of the <hi>Nazarens;</hi> and when <hi>Tertulus</hi> the <hi>Oritor,</hi> which the <hi>High prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> brought, to carry on their <hi>deceit</hi> in a <hi>plawſable manner,</hi> had laid down their <hi>falſe accuſations,</hi> the (<hi>high Prieſts, Elders</hi> and) <hi>Iews</hi> aſſented to the ſame, ſaying they were ſo.</p>
                  <p>Then <hi>Paul,</hi> after <hi>Poelex</hi> the <hi>Iudge</hi> had beckned to him to ſpeak, he <hi>answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> the more <hi>cheerfully</hi> for himſelf, and to <hi>clear</hi> his <hi>innocency,</hi> and make their <hi>accuſations</hi> appear to be <hi>falſe;</hi> he let the <hi>Iudge</hi> underſtand, <hi>that there were but twelv days ſince he went down to Ieruſalem to worſhip,</hi> &amp; letting him underſtand the whole matter, <hi>that there was no ſuch thing done by him, as they had laid down in their accuſations againſt him, neither could they prove the things whereof they accuſed him:</hi> And <hi>Foelex</hi> who ſate <hi>Iudge,</hi> hearing theſe things,<note place="margin">Act. <hi>23.23.</hi> to the end.</note> that he might act according to Law, deferred til <hi>Liſſius</hi> the <hi>chief Captain</hi> ſhould come that he might know the uttermoſt of their matter, and commanded that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould be kept til he came;<note place="margin">Act. <hi>34.1.</hi> to the <hi>24.</hi> verſe.</note> he alſo commanded the <hi>Centurion</hi> that kept him, <hi>to let him have liberty, and that he ſhould not forbid or hinder any of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance to miniſter or come unto him.</hi> By all this you may learn how to act and do in ſuch caſes, whoſe <hi>unrighteous</hi> acting againſt (<hi>Anne Audland, Iane VVaugh, Sarah Times, Nathaniel VVeſton, &amp;c.</hi>) the Servants of the Lord,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115594:6"/>that gives not the liberty to them, that the <hi>Heathens</hi> did to Chriſtians in former ages.</p>
                  <p>One <hi>Sarah Tims,</hi> who had been <hi>impriſoned</hi> in <hi>Banbury eleven weeks,</hi> who met the <hi>Prieſt</hi> in the <hi>Grave-yard,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n, fear the Lord (in obedience to his command)</hi> not uttering abuſe to any, and when ſhe had ſo ſpoken, the <hi>rude multitude</hi> hurried her, and ſtruck her with their hands, others <hi>kicked</hi> her, and <hi>ſtoned her with ſtones;</hi> and <hi>Iohn Auſtine</hi> being <hi>Mayor,</hi> and other <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> there preſent, rebuked not the <hi>rude company,</hi> as is certified in a <hi>Letter,</hi> and ſent in writing to the <hi>Prieſt</hi> &amp; <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in <hi>Banbury;</hi> &amp; after ſhe was <hi>beaten</hi> &amp; <hi>abuſed,</hi> ſhe was ſent to the Priſon, though no Law was by her broken, as did appear at her examination at the <hi>Aſſizes</hi> or <hi>Seſſions</hi> at <hi>Banbury,</hi> the day as aforeſaid; and being called to the Bar, appearing, it was asked to give in <hi>Sureties</hi> for her <hi>good behaviour,</hi> ſo ſhe deſired to know firſt what Law ſhe had tranſgreſſed, and what they had againſt her, to which they anſwered, <hi>if ſhe would not give in ſureties, ſhe ſhould to priſon again;</hi> then ſhe deſired to know by what law they committed her, and one <hi>Iohn Austine,</hi> called Mayor, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>that ſweeping the houſe, and waſhing the diſhes was the firſt point of law to her</hi> (or words to that effect) ſo ſent her back again to the Priſon, ſhe not being charged with the breach of any Law, nor witneſs brought in againſt her: but it wil be hard for any to believe theſe things, who were not eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the in, that ſuch in juſtice ſhould be acted in this Nation, where there hath bin ſo much <hi>freedom</hi> and <hi>liberty of conſcience</hi> talked of.</p>
                  <p>Then one <hi>Nathaniel VVeſton,</hi> an inhabitant in the ſaid Town, was called to the Bar, who had bin commanded by the Lord to go to the <hi>Steeplehouſe</hi> in <hi>Banbury,</hi> where the <hi>people</hi> were aſſembled together, whil'ſt the <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the Town (called <hi>Samuel VVells</hi>) was ſpeaking to them, who ſuddenly gave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>preaching</hi> (as they call it) and ſpoke twice ſo the <hi>people,</hi> ſaying, <hi>there was one, he feared, come into the congregation, which would breed a diſturbance,</hi> and he called to ſome to take him forth, for he ſaid, <hi>he could not proceed to prayer whileſt he was there;</hi> then one <hi>VVilliam VVheatly,</hi> a <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> with others, haled him forth of the <hi>ſynagogue,</hi> or <hi>ſteeplehouſe,</hi> and afterward <hi>Nathaniel VVeſton</hi> being ſent for before the Mayor, was tendred the Oath of <hi>Abjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> when in their <hi>conſciences</hi> they might know he was never addicted to <hi>pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but alwaies an <hi>enemy</hi> to their Opinions, and from his childhood obſerved, (and to them wel known, being born and bred in the ſaid Town, and was accounted) to be a ſtrict profeſſor of that which was accounted <hi>the reformed religion,</hi> and continued a diligent <hi>hearer</hi> of thoſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> who were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>godlieſt</hi> and <hi>ſtricteſt</hi> in their converſation, till of late, in the light of Chriſt Jeſus, he ſaw them to be out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereof; and although they preached to others, yet themſelves were as caſt-awaies, not living the life of them who are declared of in the Scriptures to be the Servants of God and Miniſters of Chriſt, but live in the pride and covetouſneſs, in the ſtrife and envying, and in the love and luſt, cuſtomes and vanities of the world, (and preaching by their converſation the ſame things)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115594:6"/>things) being thereunto guided by a Spirit of deceit, which is the <hi>reaſon</hi> their <hi>hearers</hi> live ſo <hi>wickedly,</hi> and ſo they are loved and upheld by the <hi>wicked</hi> world, and the <hi>love</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> they know not who live in ſuch <hi>practiſes;</hi> therefore all <hi>people</hi> behold and ſee (if you can) the ſubtil <hi>enmity</hi> of this <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> to be the ſame that ever was againſt the <hi>true worſhippers of God in Spirit,</hi> who uſe all unjuſt wayes and means as the <hi>ſerpents ſeed</hi> ever did, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to <hi>accuſe</hi> and <hi>perſecute</hi> the <hi>innocent.</hi> And although it cannot be unknown to the <hi>Magistrates</hi> of the <hi>town</hi> of <hi>Banbury,</hi> that <hi>papiſts</hi> live in it, yet when was it ever known that they tendred the Oath of Abjuration unto them, as if it were for no other end, but a <hi>ſnare</hi> to entrap the <hi>innocent;</hi> but the Lord God in his power is riſen, and into the pit muſt they go, which for others they have digged, and a juſt reward ſhall they receive from the hands of the Lord, whom we know liveth, and wil plead the cauſe of the innocent: and although the ſaid <hi>Nathaniel VVeſton,</hi> when the Oath of Abjuration was tendred to him, did utterly renounce and deny there openly, all things contained in the ſaid Oath, and witneſſed againſt all <hi>popery, popiſh,</hi> and <hi>Ieſuiticall opinions,</hi> or <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents</hi> whatſoever; and told them, that in obedience to the command of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>ſwear not at all,</hi> he could not ſwear, leſt he ſhould go out of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, in which he did abide; yet notwithſtanding was he ſent to the Priſon, where he had lain 14. <hi>weeks</hi> at their <hi>Aſſize</hi> or <hi>Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> holden in <hi>Banbury,</hi> who was there called, and appearing before them it was demanded of him, to put in <hi>ſureties</hi> for his <hi>good-behaviour,</hi> whereupon he deſired to know what Law he had <hi>tranſgreſſed,</hi> which they would not, neither was there any appeared that laid any misdemeanour or breach of law to his charge, nevertheleſs was he ſent to the priſon, where he doth yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main: So all people that hear and read theſe things, you may ſee with what juſtice the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of <hi>Banbury</hi> proceeded againſt the <hi>innocent,</hi> and <hi>ſervants</hi> of the living God.</p>
                  <p>So there was one <hi>Robert Rich</hi> (as many others) ſtanding by, who with them was an <hi>eye witneſs</hi> to many of theſe things thus acted, as before is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in their <hi>proceedings</hi> that day, and ſaw that there was great <hi>Rage</hi> in them againſt the <hi>Innocent,</hi> and how they <hi>plotted</hi> and took <hi>Counſell</hi> together againſt the <hi>ſervants</hi> of God, (laying <hi>traps</hi> and <hi>ſnares</hi> to catch them,) and after they had conſulted together, one of the Magiſtrates there ſitting on the Bench (called <hi>Thomas Hathead</hi>) ſaid to the Judg, and to ſome of the reſt of the Magiſtrates, I ſuſpect them to be Jeſuits, whenas that in his conſcience would tel him the contrary, and that out of his Envy he accuſed them, and deſired to have them tryed by the Oath of Abjuration (who in obedience to Chriſt Ieſus durſt not ſwear, to tranſgreſs his Doctrine, and break his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,) ſo at length they agreed together, and gave order to have them brought into the Court, and then the Lord God moved the aforeſaid <hi>Robert Rich</hi> to declare unto them their unjuſt proceedings, ſo according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lord, he ſpake and ſaid, that he was a Witneſs for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord God, againſt their unjuſt proceedings in the Court that day, who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115594:7"/>deſired to ſpeak, and to clear his Conſcience unto them, whereupon the Iudg and others on the Bench, bad him come up and ſpeak, and when he was come up and began to ſpeak, they cryed away with him, away with him; pull him down, pull him down; ſo their Officers, as was commanded them, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him down, and haled the ſaid <hi>Robert Rich</hi> to priſon, not permitting him to ſpeak, as they had promiſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things are written and publiſhed to the world, that people may not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how unjuſtly the innocent Lambs and ſervants of Chriſt Ieſus ſuffer, and are perſecuted in this Nation, which exceeds the perſecutions that were in former ages, either by the jews, or from thoſe in Queen</hi> Mary's <hi>dayes, for they had a Law gave them power, according to which they acted, (ſo the more to be excuſed;) but this Nation hath no ſuch perſecuting Law in force, and Liberty of conſcience hath been proclaimed, and pretended, yet men and women are beaten, buffetted, haled, ſtoned and ſtocked, and after that thrown into priſon, holes and dungeons (the breach of no known Law proved againſt them) and not ſo much freedome afforded them in priſon, as to thieves and murtherers, whoſe friends are not kept from viſiting them, as hath been known in</hi> Banbury, <hi>&amp;c. People, lay theſe things to heart and repent, that the righteous judgement of God fall not upon you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="warning">
                     <head>A Warning from the Spirit of the Lord (in his Handmaid) <hi>Anne Audland,</hi> to the Prieſt and perſecuting people in <hi>Banbury,</hi> and all ſuch as may be found in their nature, and falſly accuſing and impriſoning the Servants of the Lord Ieſus.</head>
                     <p>ALthongh I was unjuſtly impriſoned at the firſt in the town of <hi>Banbury,</hi> for no other thing but ſpeaking the truth, as in a true Declaration of the ſuffering of the innocent, who are hated without a cauſe may be ſeen, as it is declared in a printed paper, which was a Letter ſent to <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Allen,</hi> called <hi>Iuſtice of peace;</hi> With an anſwer to the falſe accuſations char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the innocent, wherein their proceedings are laid open, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be contrary to the Scriptures; as alſo their proceedings at the laſt Aſſize or Seſſions holden at <hi>Banbury,</hi> the 26. day of the 7. month, 1655. Where I was called to a tryall after long impriſonment or bonds, and there in the Court an Indictment was read againſt me, charging me with blaſphemy, and on they did proceed, called a Iury, and brought in their witneſſes, which differed one from the other, and was in confuſion, though they pretended to bear witneſs to one and the ſame thing, and falſly was I accuſed, as it did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115594:7"/>appear, when the Iury gave in their verdict, they found no blaſphemy, though for it I was accuſed, as the unchriſtian proceedings may further be ſeen both in the printed paper, (called, <hi>The ſufferings of the innocent;</hi>) &amp; in what before is ſaid in this Book, about my Examination and Tryall, which is plainly made manifeſt dayly, yet more in theſe things before mentioned, and in many other things which are committed, for which the righteous Iudg of all the world wil deal righteouſly, and call you all to an account, and weigh you in an equall ballance, and meaſure you in a juſt meaſure,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. <hi>Rom</hi> 2.5, &amp; 6.</note> and from the hand of the Lord ſhall you receive a reward according to your deeds, good weight, preſſed down, and running over, ſuch meaſure as you meeted; and in the day of your calamity an outſide profeſſion in words, when you live not in obedience to the Lord, will not hide you and cover you, and although I may be accounted as your Enemy for ſpeaking the truth, yet once again I do warn you, as from the Lord to repent,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18, 19, &amp; 27, 28, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.6. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
                        <hi>and turn from the evill of your wayes; if there be any Remembrance of your latter end,</hi> when you muſt come to be judged according to the Light in your Conſciences, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in you bears witneſs againſt deceit and unrighteouſneſs, envy, wrath, and perſecution, for which things the wrath of God comes upon the children of Diſobedience; and becauſe iudgement is not ſpeedily executed upon you, do not think you ſhall eſcape, for (your deeds are written in a Book of Remembrance, and) the Book of Conſcience willl be opened and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked muſt not go unpuniſhed. Oh ye fooliſh people and without underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding How long wil ye walk after your own inventions?<note place="margin">Ier. <hi>5.21.</hi> and to the end. Act. <hi>7.51, 52.</hi>
                        </note> How long wil ye harden your hearts againſt the Lord? How long wil ye reſiſt his Holy Spirit? Ye ſtiff-necked and Uncircumciſed in heart and ears, how long wil it be ere you return to him who hath often ſmitten you? ſhal the innocent alwaies be your mark to ſhoot at? and will you make a prey upon the harmleſs Lambs of Jeſus Chriſt? truly you will be found as ſtubble before the fire, and as duſt before the wind, <hi>the whirlwind from the Lord God is gone forth, which will ſcatter the wicked, and the fire is kindled which will conſume you;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.19, 20. <hi>Mal:</hi> 4.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.29, 30, 31, 32, 33, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13, 14, 15.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.34. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3, 4</note> 
                        <hi>thus ſaith the Lord God unto you, ye hypocrites and diſſemblers, who make a profeſſion of my name but not in truth; and calls upon me, but not in righteouſneſsl and dcaws neer me with your mouth, and enquires after me, like a people that did delight in upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whenas your hearts are far from me; Your ears are heavy, and your eyes are dim, and them whom I ſent to warn you in my name to repent, and ceaſe from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, ye will not receive, but ye impriſon ſome, and ſhamefully entreat others, and ſame ye ſend empty away; and ſo ye haſten to fill up the meaſure of your iniquity, the leaſt of you is a bryar, and the moſt upright ſharper then a thorn hedge, and ye refuſe to return, therefore ſhall trouble come upon you, as pain upon a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in travell, and miſery ſhall come upon you as an armed man: Do you think the Trumpet is ſounded, and the Allarum given for nothing, or will you gather together your ſelves againſt me, and ſet the bryers and thorns in battel? the fire is kindled which will go through you, and conſume you together, for your tranſgreſſion is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed before me, ſaith the Lord, judgement is turned away backward, truth is faln
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115594:8"/>in your ſtreets,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.14, 15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.15, 16. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.13, 14, 15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.25, 26. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> 
                        <hi>and equity cannot enter, therefore ſaith the Lord God, I will plead with you, and I wil judge amongſt the Judges, and ſan the Nations, and clenſe the land of evil doers, and the wicked wil I overturne, and cut off head and tayle; the ancient and honourable he is the head, and the Prophet that propheſies lyes, he is the tayle; and Root and Branch ſhal be conſumed,</hi> the Lord hath ſpoken it, and will raiſe up Judges as at the firſt, and Counſels as at the beginning, and the ancient of dayes ſhall rule, and the Saints of the moſt high God ſhall take the Kingdom, and the Dominion ſhall be the Lords: The Lord of Hoſts will accompliſh his word by his mighty power and outſtretched aim: Therefore now Magiſtrates, people and Prieſt, take warning while you have time and return; conſider of it, what account can you give in the day of your calamity? How wil you ſtand before the righteous Judge, and to him anſwer it, your perſecuting the innocent, and your ſhamefully entreating the harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs? Ye devouring wolves,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46.</note> who would tear the poor Lambs of Jeſus, how wil you ſtand before the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> it they ſhall depart into utter darkneſs that viſits not Chriſts little ones in priſon? How ſhall thoſe eſcape that caſts them into priſon? And in as much as you do it to one of the leaſt of his, ye do it unto him, and better had it been for you that a Milſtone had been hanged about your necks, and you drowned in the depth of the Sea, than to have offended the little ones of Jeſus Chriſt. My Conſcience I do clear unto you, in the preſence of the Lord God, in vain do you dig deep to hide your counſel from him; in vain do you gather together againſt the Lord, the burthenſome ſtone which you have taken upon you, will grind you to pieces; to the light in all your conſciences do I ſpeak, which wil wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for God, and againſt all unrighteouſneſs, in the day of the Lord, when his righteous judgements ſhall be revealed from heaven againſt all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men, and every tongue ſhall confeſs the Lord is juſt, and his wayes equall; and the witneſs in all conſciences ſhall anſwer his judgments; ſo in love to your ſouls, faithfully is the word of the Lord ſpoken unto you, and a lamentation there is over you, becauſe you reject the day of your vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation: Remember you are once more warned in your life time, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, who waits in the wil of God, patiently to come through the tryall, &amp; following the Lamb in the tribulation,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1, 2, <hi>&amp;</hi> 13, 14. <hi>ver. Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.65, 66.</note> having fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt in his ſufferings, who endured the Croſs and deſpiſed the ſhame, and by the envious Generation was called a Blaſphemer, and in the dayes of his fleſh, when he had offered up prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong cryings, and tears unto him, that was able to ſave him from death, and was heard in that he feared, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7, 8, 9.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>A. A.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115594:8"/>
                  <head>A TESTIMONY Againſt Falſe Prophets, and falſe Teacher: And alſo the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection anſwered, concerning the woman forbidden to ſpeak in the Church With a Relation of <hi>Margret Vivers,</hi> was moved of the Lord to go ſpeak to the Prieſt in the Steeplehouſe in <hi>Banbury:</hi> And alſo concerning the impriſonment of <hi>Richard Farnſworth, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>UPon the firſt day of the week, being the 3<hi rend="sup">0</hi>. day of the 7. month, one <hi>Margret Vivers,</hi> a ſervant of the Lord, (inhabiting in the Town of Banbury) was moved of the Lord to go in to the Synagogue, or Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plehouſe in the ſaid Banbury, and waited upon the Lord, whoſe power mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her to go to be ordered by him, who worketh after the counſell of his own will; and when the Prieſt of Banbury (<hi>Samuel Wells</hi> by name, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Miniſter) had ended and done, ſhe was moved of the Lord to ſpeak ſomthing unto him who had in his Doctrine, or preachment, been ſpeaking againſt ſelf-denyal, and exhorting his people that they that had not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit might pray for it; ſaying moſt of them remained in unbelief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Prayers of the wicked is abomination unto the Lord, and ſuch as are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Spirit of Chriſt (and have it not) are none of his, and they are the wicked that are in unbelief, and the enviors, mockers, ſcoffers,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28, 29. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66 18. <hi>Iud.</hi> 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26, 27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10, 11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22.23.</note> and ſuch as walk after their own ungodly luſts, who are perſecutors of the ſervants or Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, like thoſe (malicious wicked ones, and unbelievers) here at Banbury, and whileſt you regard iniquity in your hearts, God wil not regard your prayers; and to ſpeak againſt ſelf-denyal, is to ſpeak againſt the Doctrine of Chriſt, ſo no ſelf-denyall in obedience to the Doctrine of Chriſt, no Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or follower of Chriſt, and no Diſciple, no Saint; for ſaith Chriſt, he that wil be my Diſciple, let him deny himſelf and take up his Croſs and follow me, here the neceſſity is laid down by Chriſt himſelf, therefore he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth not ſelf, in obedience to Chriſt to follow his light, but continues in ſin and unbelief, abiding in darkneſs, is (no Saint but a Servant of ſin, and ſo) out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and he that abides in darkneſs, ſpeaking againſt ſelf-denyall, ſaying it makes no Saint, (though in obedience to the Spirit and word of God) he is a contradictor of the truth, and a denyer of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and neither knoweth a Saint nor him that ſanctifieth, but is ignorant of the turn and the Apoſtles Doctrine, who ſaith, ſeeing you have purified your ſouls in obeying the truth through the Spirit, love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother with a pure heart fervently, being born again (contrary to ſelf, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115594:9"/>the corruptible ſeed) for witneſſing him that ſanctifieth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.12.</note> and that which diſcovereth ſin and ſelf in the ground of it, with its fruits and effects, which is the true light of Chriſt who calls to repentance, and a denyall both of ſin and ſelf, and in obedience to his call, ſuch as follow his light are thereby led out both of darkneſs and ſelf, out of ſelf-love, ſelf-ſeeking, ſelf-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all unbelief and ſinfulneſs, as wel as out of ſelf-righteouſneſs, error, deluſion, and deceit; and into the love and joy of the Lord, righteouſneſs, peace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo into the marvellous light, even the light of life, according to the word of the Lord, in obedience thereunto, through the working of the Spirit and power of God; but ſuch as are ſervants of ſin, and do not envy ſelf, but diſobeyeth the light of him that ſanctifieth, they are in the unrighteouſneſs, denying the Doctrine of Chriſt, and turns perſecutors of them that deny ſelf in obedience to him, as their fruits maketh manifeſt (who continue in felſe undenyed) as wel as the Prieſts (anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian or) falſe Doctrine, for after the Prieſt of Banbury had been ſpoken unto for the ſame, inſtead of vindicating by Scripture what he had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red contrary to truth, when he was ſpoken to for it, he ſuffered the ſervants of the Lord Jeſus (as antichriſtians aforetime did) to be haled out of the Synagogue, and haled down to the Goalers houſe, attended with a great company of people which, ſhewed much rudeneſs and wildneſs, &amp; what little effect their Miniſtry had wrought, and ſo it were a clear manifeſtation that they were unbelievers, and thoſe that regarded iniquity in their hearts, and lived in ſin, and ſelf undenyed, and were not guided by the ſpirit of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt, as perſecutors and ſuch in their nature aforetime were, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Afterwards, one was moved to go down to the Goalers houſe, to the friend that was in cuſtody at that time, and ſome they puſhed and abuſed him, and ſome others began to reaſon with him, and would have had the Steeplehouſe to be the Church, but could not prove it ſo to be; and there they ſhewed again that their Prieſts Miniſtry had neither taught them civility nor good-behaviour, that were ſo wild and disboiſt, neither had his Miniſtry taught them (as was ſaid) to know what the Church of Chriſt was, for the Church is the body, of which Chriſt is head, and he is the head of the body his Church,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.18, 19.</note> as the Scripture witneſſeth, but Steeplehouſes are not the body of which Chriſt is head, neither is Chriſt the head of the body of Steeplehouſes (as he is of his Church (therefore the Steeplehouſes are not Chriſts church, and yet poor deluded creatures, have been taught by the Prieſts to believe that <hi>ſteeplehouſes</hi> are churches, and ſo they call them, and reſts in the periſhing and viſibles, that are ſo ignorant of the true church, the pillar and ground of truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.21, 22. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25, 26, 32. ver.</p>
                  <p>And after that when they had confeſſed that they had <hi>Margret Vivers,</hi> (who had ſpoken to the Prieſt in the <hi>Steeplehouſe,</hi> after that he had ended that day) there, neither for whoredome, felony, nor theft, and words to that purpoſe, yet it was the Mayors mind that ſhe ſhould be there; but whether
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115594:9"/>ſhe had committed any offence or no, they could not tel, (as they ſaid, and words to that effect;) and the man that kept her there upon ſuch uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when they was about to put her in Priſon, and had her at the dore, but did not put her in; for no Law by her was tranſgreſſed at that time, as it was ſaid, that could be proved for witneſſing the truth in obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lord; (yet though they did not commit herto Priſon, other two they did, one that ſtood by, and another that was quietly paſſing up the ſtreet at that ſame time) and the man that had kept her in cuſtody, did object againſt a woman ſpeaking in the Church; it was asked whether the Spirit of God might not be permitted to ſpeak in the Temple of God, yea or nay; the which by ſome was anſwered and granted that it might.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To the Queſtion about the woman forbidden to ſpeak in the Church, and proved that the ſpirit of God may ſpeak in his <hi>Temple,</hi> either in the Body of <hi>male</hi> or <hi>female, let the woman keep ſilence in the Church,</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>and let God ſpeak by his ſpirit in his Temple,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Either of male or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, whoſe bodies are the Temples of God through the spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>For in Chriſt Ieſus the ſpirit of God in male and female is both one, Eph.</hi> 2.19.19, 20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27, 28. And <hi>Paul</hi> he commended <hi>Pheba</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Romans, which <hi>Phebe</hi> was a ſervant of the Church which was at <hi>Cenchrea, Rom.</hi> 16.1. and in the ſame Epiſtle he ſaluted <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> and alſo gave thanks with the Churches for her labour, who had been a helper of him in Chriſt Jeſus, and ſhe was a woman labourer in the Goſpel by the Spirit of truth; ſo was there woman labourers with <hi>Paul</hi> in the Goſpell, which he writes of in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> as wel as them he ſpeaks of, whoſe names are written in the book of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.3, 4. <hi>Phi.</hi> 4.3.</p>
                  <p>So was there women guided by the Spirit of the Lord, that were the Lords Propheteſſes, as wel as there were men that were his Prophets; and the Lord ſpoke his word by his own Spirit, in and through the one as wel as the other: <hi>Miriam, Arons</hi> Siſter, was a Propheteſs, and ſpake forth the praiſe of God, in that diſpenſation and adminiſtration, by the ſpirit of God that teacheth to prophenſie, as wel as the manifeſtation of it is given to profit withall, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20, 21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.16, 17, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Deborah</hi> a Propheteſs by the Spirit of the Lord which taught her to propheſie, ſhe therewith judged Iſrael, and were a Miniſter of Juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Lords people in her dayes, and in that diſpenſation, inſomuch, that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came up to her for judgment, and did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the counſell of the Lords ſpirit in a woman preacher, or a <hi>Iudge</hi> in <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and a <hi>Propheteſs</hi> of the Lord, <hi>Iudg.</hi> the 4, 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in the dayes of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there was one <hi>Huldah</hi> a <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs,</hi> that lived in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> a <hi>woman Preacher,</hi> or one, who by the Spirit of the Lord, declared and ſpoke to the people the word of the Lord, and to her the Prieſt and people went to enquire and hear the word of the Lord, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording alſo to the Kings command, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, &amp;c. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſeveral other <hi>Propheteſſes</hi> as wel as <hi>Prophets,</hi> there was in the time of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115594:10"/>old among the Lords people,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſſa.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Nebe.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29, 30, 31, 32.</note> as the <hi>propheteſs</hi> in <hi>Iſajahs</hi> time, and in <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miahs</hi> time, ſo there was in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time a man in <hi>Ceſaria</hi> had four <hi>daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> that were virgins did <hi>propheſie, Act.</hi> 21.8, 9. And at the comming of Chriſt when <hi>Simeon</hi> that juſt man ſpoke of him, <hi>the light of the Gentiles and the glory of the people Iſrael,</hi> there was one woman a widow, of above fourſcore years of age, that had no outward huuſband at home to ask, who was a <hi>preacher,</hi> or one that ſpoke of the Lord Ieſus to all that looked for Redemption in <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Luke</hi> 2.36, 37, 38.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Tryphena,</hi> and <hi>Tryphoſa,</hi> and <hi>Perſis</hi> (three vertuous godly women) did labour much in the Lord, which <hi>Paul</hi> (in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi>) did ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; and as the wife is in ſubjection to her husband, ſo is the Church ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto Chriſt, who is the head thereof, as the husband is the head of the wife; and Chsiſt being the Head of his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> or <hi>husband</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of Chriſt united unto him, and betrothed in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> both as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of him, and ſtaying at home taketh counſell with him, though the Harlot from home, and the ſtranger unto him, knoweth it not; and ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>el</hi> 2.28, 6.</note> I <hi>wil pour out of my ſpirit, that ſons, and daughters, and handmaids alſo ſhall propheſie;</hi> and who are they that are offended hereat now? that the Lord doth ſee, but <hi>proud, covetous, ſelf-ſeeking prieſts,</hi> (who never knew God,) and their <hi>hearers</hi> that are deceived by them, and ſuch in their nature who know not the ſure word and ſpirit of <hi>propheſie,</hi> but are ignorant both of the <hi>myſtery</hi> of <hi>godlineſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 17.8.</note> and ſo of him whoſe name is called <hi>the word of God,</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neither the <hi>teachings</hi> of God, not the life of the Scriptures, and the work of the Spirit of God, who would not have him to be the ſame now that he was, and Chriſt to be the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever; who are ſuch oppoſers of the work of the Spirit of God, and perſecutors of the ſervants of Jeſus, in whom it is bringing and brought forth, as their Generation and ſeed of evil doers ever was; <hi>Mat,</hi> 23.33, 34, &amp;c.
<q>Holy men of God ſpoke forth the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Scriptures or Writings that proceeded from the Spirit of truth, were not ſpoken forth by the ſeed of evill doers, that were haters of God, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuters of his, neither were they ſpoken forth by ſuch as preached for Hire, barerule by their means,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pel,</hi> 1.21. <hi>Ier.</hi> 26.9, 10. <hi>Ier</hi> 20.2 <hi>Ier.</hi> 37.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> nor ſuch as laid heavy burthens upon the people, &amp; ſought for their gain from their quarter, (like the Prieſts of England, the falſe prophets, and phariſees) but Holy men of God, who witneſſed againſt ſuch, ſpoke forth the Scriptures, as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, who were perſecuted, mocked, ſtoned, haled out of the Synagogues, ſet in the Stocks, moſt ſhamefully abuſed, evilly entreated, and ſore puniſhed, ſmitten, put in the Dungeon, and often impriſoned, and ſuch a portion from the world and ſeed of evill doers doth the ſervants and meſſengers of God meet withall now, that witneſs againſt them, who make a trade upon their words, alſo denying them, and owning the teachings of God, and the life of the Scriptures again now, as they that ſpoke them forth, who ſuffered for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing the truth in the life and power of them aforetime did.</p>
                  <div type="account">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115594:10"/>
                     <head>A ſhort Relation betwixt the true Prophets and the falſe, and how they may be known a ſſunder.</head>
                     <p>Firſt, THe true <hi>Prophets</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> had the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> revealed to, and inſpired in them, and the moving cauſe of their ſpeaking, was from the <hi>light, life</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> within them, who dwelt in the <hi>light</hi> which diſcovered <hi>deceit,</hi> whereby they know the falſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and declared againſt them, and againſt ſuch as ſpoke the words of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.16, 17. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.</note> ſaying <hi>thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> when the Lord ſpoke not unto them, or by them, and ſo they ſpeak a Divination of their own brain, (as do the Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Prieſts and Deceivers) and not from the mouth of the Lord, as to thoſe that dwel in the <hi>light,</hi> as the true Prophets did, they now are very wel, known, and againſt teſtified, though it be not received by the beſotted, turned from the <hi>light;</hi> and the deceived, who perſecutes thoſe that are ſent to witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them (contrary to the wil of man) as the true Prophets were, who were not ſent by the wil of man, but by the Lord God and his ſpirit, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.16, 17. <hi>which the world could not receive,</hi> nor the wil of man, no more than it doth now, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17 and therefore do they perſecute, and put out of their Synagogues, for to fil up the meaſure of their iniquity, and to fulfil the <hi>propheſie</hi> of Chriſt, ye a theſe things they do, becauſe they are in enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the living truth, and know neither the father nor the Son, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2.3. and ſo manifeſt what an evil and a wicked Generation they are on.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The true Prophets of God, who were indued with his ſpirit, and dwelt in the light, and ſpoke as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, and were not ſent of man (contrary to the wil of God,) but of God, (contrary to the wil of man;) and ſuch as are ſent by the Lord God and his ſpirit now, have their commander neer them, and by his holy Spirit are moved to ſpeak as he pleaſeth, and as they was, who were not ſent by the wil of man, neither did mans wil receive them that went contrary to it (and ſtood in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God) no more than it doth now, but rather perſecured and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as they do now; and the true Prophets that were ſent of the Lord, and ſtoood in his counſell, neither preached for hire, nor ſought for their gain from their quarter, nor ſought for the fleece, but preached or declared free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the word of the Lord, and ſaid, come freely without money or price <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. And alſo declared againſt the deceit of the falſe Prophets, and hireling Prieſts, and ſuch as ſought for their gain from their quarter, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. And the true prophets declared againſt ſuch as cryed peace, peace, to the people whileſt they put into their mouths, but when they could not for conſcience ſake uphold them in their deceits, nor put into their mouths, then the falſe prophets, and ſuch as preached for hire, either ſhut up in priſon or prepared war againſt them, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.5.11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.9.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> And the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115594:11"/>falſe prophets and Hireling prieſts do the ſame now,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iude</hi> 11.</note> and therefore they walk in their fore-fathers ſteps, and are known by their fruits, which is marks; and the way to know them by according as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15, 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. And the true prophet that ſtood in the counſel of God &amp; preached or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, and declared the word of the Lord freely, they neither perſecuted, impriſoned, nor cauſed any to be perſecuted and impriſoned, as the (falſe prophets and) prieſts that ſtood not in the counſel of God aforetime did, as wel as their off-ſpring hireling Prieſts, falſe prophets, and ſeed of evil doers do now:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.30, 31.</note> 
                        <hi>Ieremiah</hi> was a true prophet, and were ſent of the Lord to declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the falſe, and againſt ſuch as bore rule by their means, and held up the filthy and horrible thing, which he then ſaw committed in the Land, as the falſe prophets and hireling prieſts do now; and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the true prophet neither put others in the Stocks, nor perſecuted and impriſoned any, but he himſelf were perſecuted and impriſoned, put in the Dungeon, and ſet in the Stocks in the high gate of <hi>Benjamen, Ier.</hi> 20. And when <hi>Ieremiah</hi> went to the Cities of Judah, who were in the diſobedient nature, and come up then (to worſhip) the Lord commanded <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to go ſtand in the Court, and ſpeak to them the words which he commanded him to ſay, without dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of them, and he did ſo in obedience to the command of the Lord, then the Prieſts asked him why he had ſpoken ſuch words, and they were ſore of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at him for it, that they judged him worthy of death, and ſaid he ſhould ſurely dye, and ſo ſought to take away his life for it, and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Prieſts and their party that were ſo in rage againſt him for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the truth, and ſaid unto them, <hi>As for me, behold, I am in your hands, as for me, do with me as ſeemeth good and meet unto you, but (be ſure, or) know ye for certain, that if ye put me to death, ye ſhall ſurely bring innocent blood both upon your ſelves and upon your City, and the inhabitants thereof, and of a truth the Lord hath ſent me to ſpeak all theſe words in your ears:</hi> Jer. 26. <hi>Ye perſecutors and blood-thirſtie ones, who cannot receive the truth that bears teſtimony againſt your deceit, but ſeeks the blood of the innocent,</hi> the perſecuting prieſts and their party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foretime did, from whence you are ſprung; ſtop your mouths, cover your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and bluſh, obſerve your root, and ſee both the fruits of the perſecuting prieſts and their party. And likewiſe behold your Spirit, and repent of your cruelty &amp; madneſs (at <hi>Banbury</hi>) for there is like prieſt like people, as ſaith the Prophet: <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9. <hi>And as a troop of Robbers wait for a man, ſo the company of Prieſts murder in the way by conſent,</hi> as it is written and witneſſed, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.9.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115594:11"/>
                  <head>The Prieſts crueltie manifeſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVHen Chriſt Jeſus (the Dear Son of God) came <hi>to teſtifie againſt the world, that the deeds thereof was evill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>Mark</hi> 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. &amp; 27 <hi>chap.</hi>
                     </note> the Prieſts and their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty held <hi>counſells againſt him, and ſought falſe witneſs to take away his life,</hi> and they accuſed him for blaſphemy, and ſaid, <hi>what further need had they of witneſs againſt him? Herod</hi> alſo, and his men of war, <hi>they ſet him at nought;</hi> and both <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> became friends to joyn perſecution againſt him, and that evill ſeed had their hands in ſhedding his innocent blood; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had done ſo by him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 18 &amp; 19 <hi>chapt. Act.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. &amp; <hi>the</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 <hi>verſes.</hi>
                     </note> his Servants were evilly entreated from the perſecuting Prieſts, and ſeed of evill doers; <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were put in the Priſon, and afterwards beaten, and commanded to ſpeak no more in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but for all that they could not but ſpeak the thing which they had heard and ſeen: And <hi>Stephen</hi> were judged by the prieſts and their counſell, to be a Blaſphemer, though he was a man ful of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; and ſo ignorant were they of the Spirit of truth, that they perſecuted them that were guided by it; and out of envy and malice &amp; ſhed innocent blood, and took away <hi>Stephens</hi> life, by ſtoning him to death as a Malefactor, under the pretence of a Blaſphemer, when no ſuch thing could be proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, though the <hi>Greeks, Libertines, Stoicks,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13, 14, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Mat.</hi> 43, <hi>to the</hi> 10. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20. <hi>Act</hi> 21.28, 29, 30, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.17, 18. &amp; 24, 25. <hi>verſ. Act.</hi> 18.12, 13, 14, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.16, 17, 18.</note> and <hi>Epicarians</hi> ſought to encounter him. And <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> he were behaedded by <hi>Herods</hi> command, though he were convinced, and knew [by that in his conſcience] that he were an <hi>upright Man.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> he were counted a <hi>Peſtilent Fellow,</hi> a <hi>mover of Sedition</hi> and a <hi>Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazarens,</hi> &amp; they cryed out, <hi>Men of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>holy, this is the man that turneth the world up-ſide-down;</hi> and they drew him out of the Temple, and forthwith, the doors were ſhut, he were beaten and abuſed for going into their Markets and Synagogues to reaſon and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with the <hi>Iews,</hi> and for teſtifying againſt the outward Temple, and that Temple-worſhip, and bearing witneſs againſt their deceits, <hi>who alſo was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of Chriſt, and both choſen and ſent, to turn people from darkneſs to the Light, and from the power of Satan unto God, Act.</hi> 26. Yet ſo blinde and ignorant of the life of truth were the Prieſts and their counſell, that they perſecuted <hi>Paul</hi> as they did the reſt, and ſaid he was a <hi>mover of ſedition,</hi> and accuſed him as a heretick, and ſought by all means to take away his life, though he told them of his chooſing and Call, Commiſſion and ſending, they could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, that knew not the Spirit by which he were guided and ſent, who alſo told them, that in the way which they called hereſie, did he worſhip the God of his Fathers; yet for all that were he impriſoned, beaten, and ſet in the Stocks:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 24.14, 15. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.22, 23 24.</note> And the ſame portion from the Prieſts and their party doth the Servants of Jeſus meet with in the world: Wo to the wicked ſeed of evill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115594:12"/>and perſecutors; Prieſt and people, you are ſeen with the Light, and you Spirits are tryed,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.4, 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> and your wayes comprehended, and all your falſe worſhips and you are found out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, &amp; in the ſteps of the <hi>falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and amongſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>phariſees, called of men Maſters, and hath the chiefe place in the Aſſembly, ſtands praying in the Synagogues, and bind heavy burdens upon the people,</hi> and grievous to be born; and as Chriſt cryed wo to your Fathers, the ſame Woes are to you their off-ſpring, who are found with their Marks, and following their ſteps, you are clearly ſeen with the light, and comprehended, and with the Light judged and condemned, though to ſome you appear like <hi>Graves</hi> which men paſs over and are not aware; wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you whited walls, and painted Sepulchers, ye ſerpents, ye generation of Vipers, how ſhall you eſcape the damnation of hel, as Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.33,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.44. <hi>ver.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. Mark</hi> 12.38, 39, 40.</p>
                  <div type="observations">
                     <head>A few Obſervations of the Lords ſending his Servants informer dayes, &amp;c.</head>
                     <p>Firſt. THE Lord God of Power, in former Ages, ſent forth his <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles, Meſſengers</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> his Spirit, in the power and life,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.3.3.</note> to deliver his <hi>maſſages</hi> and do his <hi>ſervice,</hi> to witneſs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt the world, and the wickedneſs thereof; ſome to tell the people of their ſins, and cry aloud, &amp; ſpare not, and to reprove in the Gate, and cry out againſt pride and oppreſſion, and were ſignes and wonders in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and none could believe their report and witneſs with them, where the Arm of the Lord was unrevealed, yet they might do it in obedience to the word of the Lord, though they became ſignes and wonders alſo to the <hi>world,</hi> as <hi>Iſajah</hi> was, that went naked and bare-foot three years, in obedience to the Word of the Lord, <hi>as a ſigne and wonder unto</hi> Aegypt <hi>and</hi> Ethiopia, as it is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> the 20. Chap.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Some went in obedience to the command of the Lord to cry out againſt preaching for hire, and againſt injuſtice, and judging for rewards, and not ſuffering the cauſe of the poor and needy to come before them,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.1,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, 3, 4 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.1.23, 24</note> 
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo told their Princes were rebellious, and companions of, or with thieves, as wel as their Judges were ravening wolves, and ſome amongſt them roaring Lyons; as <hi>Micah,</hi> and <hi>Zepheniah,</hi> and the Lords prophets did, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.21, 22, 23. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And ſome were ſent from one place to another, in obedience to the word and ſpirit of the Lord, and ſometimes knew to whom to go, and what to ſay; and other ſometimes they knew to whom (and whither, or where) to go, and not at that preſent time what to ſay, yet they did wel for to obey, though they ſate where thoſe they were ſent to ſate; and remained where they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115594:12"/>remained (if in ſilence) as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the Lords Prophet did,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> ſeven dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the word of the Lord came unto him what to ſay, when he was ſent to them of the Captivity of <hi>Tel-abib,</hi> that dwelt by the River <hi>Chebar;</hi> and as <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the true Prophet of the Lord, went amongſt them, in obedience to the word and ſpirit of the Lord, and ſate (ſilent) amongſt them ſeven dayes, before the word of the Lord came unto him what to ſay; it were no deluſion nor deceit: And if any of the Lords Servants, in obedience to the word and ſpirit of the Lord, ſhould be thereby guided ſo to do, they would neither be deluded nor deceived in (and by) ſo doing, no more then he was, though the world know it not (who were ever ſtrangers to the Lord;) therefore let fleſh be ſilent at the work of the Spirit of God, and all ſuch as knows not the eternall word and meſſage of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="observations">
                     <head>Who are no Vagabonds nor Ieſuits, and who are the Vaga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bonds, as herein wil appear.</head>
                     <p>Firſt, THe Miniſters of Chriſt that went up and down, preaching the word of eternall life, and were ſent to turn people from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Light, and from the power of Satan unto God, and though ſome of them might have no certain dwelling place,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.25, 26, 27. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.17. <hi>to the</hi> 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.20.</note> yet were they neither Jeſuits, Fugitives, nor Vagabond fellows, no more are ſuch as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the power of the Spirit of God that do ſo now: The Son of man, though he had not whereon to lay his head, yet he were no Fugitive, Jeſuit, nor Vagabond, nor ſuch as in obedience to the Lord, that wandred ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to and fro, and were in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skins, as wel as in dens and caves of the earth, of whom the world was not worthy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.36.37, 38. they were neither Jeſuits, Fugitives, nor Vagabonds, no more are ſuch now, to do the work of the Lord, and work in his Vineyard, whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is in God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, though they may go to and fro to preach the word of life, in obedience to the commands of the Lord, and doing his wil as he of them requireth, though contrary to the will of man, who lives in Diſobedience to the power and ſpirit of the Lord, as <hi>Cain</hi> the Fugitive and Vagabond did, and as ſuch in the envy who are in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contrary to God, and walking in <hi>Cains</hi> way now do,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19, <hi>ver. Rom.</hi> 1.27, 28. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.5.</note> and to them is the curſe and the wo, <hi>Iude</hi> 11.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 The Miniſters of Chriſt aforeſaids did witneſs againſt deceit, in ſtreets, markets, and Synagogues (yet were they neither Fugitives nor Vagabonds) though for it they were haled out, and ſtoned, perſecuted, by the chiefe Prieſts conſent, and abuſed by their party, and Vagabond fellows, who in perſecuting the truth deny the Lord, as ſuch Vagabond fellows that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akes with the chiefe Prieſts to perſecute the Saints and ſervants of Jeſus do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115594:13"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115594:13"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115594:14"/>now,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 18.4, 5, 6. <hi>Iude</hi> 11.</note> as well as the perſecuting Prieſts and Vagabond fellowes that lived in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, as their forefathers formerly did, who perſecuted the Servants of Jeſus for witneſſing the truth, and teſtifying againſt deceit, in Streets, Markets, and Synagogues, or Idolls-Temples, as their off ſpring do now, perſecute thoſe that do as the ſervants of Jeſus therein did, and againſt them they act and vent forth their envy and cruelty, by the chief Prieſts conſent, and their pratakers act, and thereby they manifeſt themſelves to be of <hi>Cains</hi> ſtock, and their ſacrifices to be rejected, as his was, who make it appear what a ſeed of evil doers, and a curſed Generation they are.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="account">
                     <head>An Account of <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi>'s Commitment to Priſon in <hi>Banbury,</hi> the 30th. of the 7th. Month; and his Examination and Anſwer, in brief, at the Court before the Mayor and Iuſtices the day following, being the firſt of the eigth Month, <hi>1655.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS he with another friend was walking peacably up the ſtreet to a friends houſe in <hi>Banbury,</hi> meeting in the <hi>ſtreet Aholiab VVeſt,</hi> called mayor, &amp; <hi>VVilliam Allen</hi> called a Juſtice, with many other people of the town, &amp;c. The ſaid Mayor and Juſtice, as aforeſaid, ſo called, came to him very much enraged, as he was walking on the Street, &amp; <hi>VVilliam Allen</hi> a Juſtice, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, belonging to the Borrough, he did ſtrike, or pluck off his hat, &amp; grinn'd at him, and heaved his fiſt in his wrath, and could ſcarce hold his hands; and then to fulfil his envie, he cryed have him away to the Stocks, the which they were doing in obedience to his will, and after they were gone from the place, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>likg him towards the Stocks, the ſaid <hi>VVilliam Allen</hi> to ſhew his confuſion in his actings, as wel as his ſelf-contradictions, he came to the men and ſaid, bring him back and have him to Priſon, and they did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, his words to diſobey, but with all expedition haled him down to the priſon out of the Street, and then <hi>(R. F.)</hi> he asked what fact he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, that deſerved either Stocks or impriſonment, and deſired of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſo called, to know the Fact and the Law, by vertue whereof the Fact became a crime, which were denyed to be made known unto him; but with violence were he haled, and thruſt into cloſe priſon, and there remaineth. The next day they held a Court, and called him before them, being the firſt day of the 8. month, 1655.</p>
                     <p>And the Mayor and Juſtices (ſo called) being ſet, and <hi>R.F.</hi> brought before them, according to their command; <hi>Aholiab VVeſt,</hi> called Mayor, he asked <hi>(R. F.)</hi> his name, and where he lived; to the which he anſwered very mlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſaid, ſaid, <hi>That as he ſtood in Relation to God, in whom his ſoul lived; and as were a witneſs of the immortall ſeed, in the Regeneration born of the Spirit, and</hi>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115594:14"/>begotten by the eternall word, which endureth for ever, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22, 23: he ſaid in that relation as he there ſtood, he had a new name given him of God, which no man knows, but he that hath it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. And as he was in Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to man, he had a name given him by man, to be known by to man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the account of the world, called in the outward by the <hi>name, Richard Farnſworth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then the Mayor asked him again where he lived; to the which he anſwered and ſaid, <hi>in the firſt place in God, (and as the Apoſtle, as wel as the Poet hath ſaid) in whom we live, move, and have our being, &amp;c.</hi> (Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.28.) Then ſaid the Mayor, But have you not a being in the world? I anſwer, ſaid he, <hi>That reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is being, my being is with the Lord; but an outward reſidence, or being I have,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>at a place called</hi> Tickhill <hi>in</hi> Yorkſhire: Then ſaid the Mayor, But how long have you been here in this Town? To the which <hi>(R. F.)</hi> he anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Four or five dayes, if not a week.</hi> The Mayor asked him what he did there, to the which he anſwered, <hi>he came to viſit his friends,</hi> &amp;c. Then the Mayor asked him where he had been ſince he came into the <hi>town;</hi> he anſwered, <hi>The moſt at</hi> Edward Vivers: then <hi>Iohn Auſtine</hi> (who is called a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, he asked him if he were the Meſſenger of God, to the which he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>There was but the Meſſengers of Chriſt and of Antichriſt (in them two rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) and the meſſage of Antichriſt he did deny.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>After that, the Mayor ſaid, how might they know that, for they might not expect Revelations now? to the which he anſwered and ſaid, Though he (to wit, the Mayor) and they did not expect Revelations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the work of the Spirit of God for being to them who did expect and wait for them, that wait for the grace which is brought unto ſuch at the revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt, according to the Apoſtles Doctrine, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 13.) <hi>For the deep things of God are revealed by the Spirit of God unto his ſervants and children,</hi> as it is written. And ſaith Chriſt (<hi>Mat.</hi> 11.21.)<note place="margin">i <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.i0. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.22.</note> No man knoweth the Son but the Father, neither knoweth any man the Father, ſave the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son wil reveal him: Then ſuch as deny Revelations by the Son, they deny the appointed way and means of attaining to the true knowledg of God the Father, and the Son. And Chriſt hath ſaid the ſame concerning the knowledg of God by Revelation, as a ſecond confirmation, in <hi>Luke</hi> (the 10.22. ver. witneſſing and agreeing with that in <hi>Matthew</hi> (the 2.27.) And <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle, not of man neither by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt and God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead, did certifie unto the brethren that the Ghoſpel which he preachnd was not of man, for he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther received of man, neither was he taught it of man, but by the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. and the 11, &amp; 12. ver. Then <hi>VVilliam Allen</hi> (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Juſtice) ſaid it was not the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt in him, but by Chriſt unto him; then <hi>(R.F.)</hi> he anſwered, that the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>when it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in</hi> him, that he might preach him among the heathen, he immediately preached him, <hi>not conferring with fleſh and blood,</hi> after he were ſo revealed in him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15.16. So there was a Revelation of Chriſt within, and after he was ſo revealed (within) in <hi>Paul,</hi> he went to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115594:15"/>
                        <hi>preach</hi> him forth among the <hi>heathen,</hi> and <hi>gentiles,</hi> and ſaid to the <hi>Colloſſians, great is the myſtery of godlineſs, Chriſt in you the hope of glory, whom we preach and teach, warning every man every where, that we may preſent them perfect in Chriſt Ieſus, Col.</hi> 1.25, 26, 27, 28. ver.</p>
                     <p>And after that there was a few words ſpoken concerning the Objection of the womans non-permiſſion, which before is anſwered; and when it was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them on the Bench, if the Spirit of God might not ſpeak in the Temple, they were then put to a ſtand, or partly ſilent about the ſame; and <hi>R.F.</hi> then and there ſaid, if any of them would deny it, he would by plain Scripture prove that the Spirit of God might ſpeak in his Temple (meaning either in the body of male or female) as aforetime it did;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.17, i7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27, 28. 2 Cor. 3.17.</note> and little was ſaid thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to at that preſent, then when <hi>R.F.</hi> was there ſpeaking about the Saints bodies being the Temples for God to dwel in, as God hath ſaid, I wil dwel in them and walk in them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. Then ſaid <hi>Iohn Auſtine,</hi> who is called a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, if God did dwel in them, he ſaid where was his legs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the which <hi>VVilliam Allen,</hi> called a Juſtice, gave a ſecret check, ſeeming to be troubled thereat: And <hi>(R.F.)</hi> he told <hi>Iohn Auſtine</hi> Juſtice (ſo called) that God was a ſpirit, and is as the Scripture witneſſeth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.23, 24. And Chriſt is a myſtery, <hi>Col.</hi> i, 26, 27. &amp; therefore it may be ſaid, <hi>that great is the myſtery of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> God manifeſt infleſh, for the would by their wiſdome cannot find it out. Read and conſider, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10, 11.</p>
                     <p>And now that I have left that place of Scripture upon you, that was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to ſuch in your natures; I ſhall come on to what was ſaid by you, in ſome things at the bench, with anſwers and enlargments thereunto by proof from the Scripture, or as followeth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aholiab VVeſt</hi> the aforeſaid Mayor of <hi>Banbury,</hi> who ſate in the Court with the two Juſtices, he asked the Town-Clerk for the Oath of Abjuration, and the Town-Clerk ſaid he had it not there, but he would go for it, the which he did, and tendred it unto <hi>(R. F.)</hi> the ſervant of the Lord, and as he read it, the ſaid <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> did in the Court there, in the preſence of God by whoſe power he were kept and upheld, utterly deny and deteſt all Popiſh wayes, and Jeſuiticall Opinions, whatſoever, and thoſe things contained in that Act, or oath of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> and ſtands a witneſs againſt all <hi>Popiſh</hi> wayes and <hi>falſe worſhips,</hi> but to <hi>Sweare,</hi> as they would have had, he ſaid he could not for <hi>Conſcience ſake</hi> do it, for it was (and is) contrary to the <hi>command</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt; then they alledged that an <hi>Oath</hi> was for the end of all ſtrife and controverſie amongſt men, which is anſwered as followeth; yea, in the time of old it was ſo, when <hi>Oaths</hi> were ordained for that end; but Chriſt (the <hi>Oath of God</hi>) ended all <hi>Oathes</hi> to his,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.33, 34, 35, 36. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.12.</note> and where <hi>ſtrife</hi> and <hi>controverſie</hi> is, there Chriſt is not yet learned, who brings <hi>good will</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> to ſuch as in his <hi>Doctrine</hi> abide, who hath ſaid, <hi>That in the time of old it was ſaid; thou ſhalt perform thine Oathes unto the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> But ſaith he now, <hi>I ſay unto you ſwear not at all, Mal.</hi> 5.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115594:15"/>
                     <p>Then it was ſaid to <hi>R.F.</hi> by one, that if he read on, he might ſee that Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, <hi>in all communications let your yea be yea, and nay, nay;</hi> to the which he anſwered the party before the <hi>bench,</hi> that he might obſerve that <hi>Yea,</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> in their places, was as binding in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> as <hi>Oathes</hi> was in the <hi>Old-Covenant,</hi> and therefore Chriſt forbad all <hi>Oathes;</hi> and now they that own Chriſt and his <hi>Doctrine,</hi> who abide therein, are to let their <hi>yea, be yea, and nay, nay:</hi> and deny all <hi>Oathes,</hi> for ſo hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> commanded; And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Above all things my Brethren, ſwear not at all, leaſt ye fall into condemnation. Iam.</hi> 5.12. <hi>But let your yea, be yea, and your nay, nay:</hi> So they that ſwear, (and they that cauſe men to do it) are in the <hi>evill,</hi> under the <hi>condemnation,</hi> and out of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That he that tranſgreſſeth, and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God;</hi> conſidder of this, 2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. <hi>But be that abideth in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath both the Father and the Son.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They alledged that the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaid they ſhould <hi>ſwear</hi> (<hi>the Lord lived,</hi> and <hi>ſwear</hi>) in righteouſneſs. Anſwer, <hi>Yea it was ſo, and there was in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets dayes that ſwore the Lord lived, and ſwore (in unrighteouſneſs, for they ſwore) falſely, as the true Prophet hath ſaid,</hi> Ier. 5.2. <hi>and though the Prophet did ſay they ſhould ſwear the Lord lived and ſwear in righteouſneſs, Chriſt Ieſus the (end of Oathes to his, and) ſubſtance of what the Prophets propheſied of, he is come, and forbids all Oathes, and ſaith,</hi> Swear not at all; <hi>and if it be alledged that</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph <hi>in</hi> Aegypt <hi>ſwore, it is anſwered, for thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> Out of <hi>Egypt</hi> have I called my Son, hear him, and he ſaith, ſwear not at all: <hi>and if it be alledged that</hi> Jacob <hi>ſwore, Chriſt he reignes over the houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>who ſaith,</hi> ſwear not at all; <hi>and if it be alledged that</hi> Solomon <hi>ſwore, I anſwer, Chriſt is greater than</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>who forbids ſwearing, and all Oathes, ſaying,</hi> ſwear not at all. And if it be alledged that the angell ſwore, <hi>true he did ſo, but thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> I bring forth my firſt born, &amp; only begotten Son, let all the Angels worſhip him, <hi>hear what he ſaith, and he forbids oathes, who ſaith,</hi> ſwear not at all, <hi>and they are Chriſts friends (as he hath ſaid) that keeps his commands; and ſaith he,</hi> if ye love me keep my commandments; <hi>and they that loved him, as his do now; ſaid,</hi> By this we know we love him, becauſe we keep his commandments; <hi>then bleſſed are they who abide in Chriſts doctrine, and ſwear not, in obedience to</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and keeps his commands, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and may enter in through the gates into the city;</hi> Rev. 22.13, 14. <hi>For the unrighteous, and ſuch as diſobey the truth, who keepeth not Chriſts commands, but lives in the tranſgreſſion, ſerving the evil, and ſo fall under the condemnation of the Devill, they and ſuch like are ſhut out of Gods Kingdome, and enters not into the holy city, as they may read; and the ſcriptures ſtands a witneſs againſt them, and all ſuch as are of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſeed, perſecuting the godly in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, 2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11. 2 Theſſ. 1.6, 7, 8, 9. 1 Cor 6.9, 10. Gal. 5.19, 20, 21. Rom. 1.27, 28, 29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rev. 20.10, &amp;c. Rev. 21.8. &amp; 27. Rev. 22.15, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>And when the ſervant of Jeſus could not break the command of Chriſt, nor tranſgreſs his Doctrine to ſwear, they ſaid they would return up his name to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115594:16"/>the <hi>Exchequer;</hi> who told them, <hi>they might do as they were ordered;</hi> then the <hi>Mayor</hi> ſaid, if he would pay his <hi>Fees</hi> and go out of the Town that night, he might go <hi>free;</hi> and <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> anſwered, who could not be a <hi>friend</hi> to <hi>deceit,</hi> that he could not pay <hi>fees</hi> for a nights falſe impriſonment, and withall, asked <hi>what Law he had broken or tranſgreſſed,</hi> and withall ſaid, <hi>if they knew any evill by him acted or done, they might there declare it,</hi> but they ſaid he juſtified himſelf, and they feared he was deceived, who bad them lay open the ground of ſelf, with the <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> of it, if they could, and <hi>convince</hi> him of it, but they ſaid they would not meddle with that, and words to that effect; and one <hi>Iohn Auſtine,</hi> called a Iuſtice, asked him whether the Spirit were created or in-created? to the which (<hi>Rich. Farnſworth</hi>) he anſwered, <hi>That the ſpirit of God, which is the Saints guide, is eternall, and they that are gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſpirit of God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12.23. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.</note> 
                        <hi>are the ſons of God, as it is written,</hi> Rom. 8.14. <hi>And God hath ſent the ſpirit of his Son into our hearts, whereby we cry</hi> abba <hi>Father,</hi> Gal. 4.6. Then the Mayor ſaid, he had need to take heed he ſpoke not <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> would he ſay that he was a ſon of God? whoſe anſwer is, That ſuch as were, and are born of the ſpirit of God, and guided thereby, are, and were, the ſons of God, that were and are ſo born. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22, 13. <hi>and guided by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God into the truth, and the Holy Vnction its ſelf. Iohn</hi> 16.13. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.20.27. And they ſaid, (as ſuch with them and the ſame ſpirit, being guided thereby, ſo may ſay) <hi>Behold! what manner of love is this that the father hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called the ſons of</hi> God? And now we are the Sons of God, <hi>therefore the world knoweth us not, becauſe it knew him not,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1. and to witneſs with the Scriptures by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> according to the work of the power and ſpirit of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to meaſure and manifeſtation (is no blaſphemy, though the Jews ſaid it was) and that may be witneſsed unto, though perſecutors and the world know it nor, nor receive it, yet he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are of him, and are of one, for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them Brethren, as it is written and witneſsed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10, 11. and when he would have diſputed the caſe with them, if they would have ſtood to Diſpute accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scripture and the work of the ſpirit of God, then Iuſtice <hi>Auſtine</hi> (ſo called) ſaid, Had he the ſame ſpirit that the apoſtles or Chriſt had? Who anſwered and ſaid, that if any man that had not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he was none of his, as they might read in <hi>Romans</hi> the 8th. and the ſpirit that the apoſtles had, or received of God, was the ſpirit of the Son, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. and of the Father, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.23.24. and Chriſt ſaid it was not them that ſpoke, but the ſpirit of their Father that ſpoke in them: then the ſaid Iuſtice <hi>Auſtine,</hi> ſo called, ſaid to <hi>R.F.</hi> hold thou thy tongue, and ſee if the ſpirit will ſpeak, to the which anſwer was given, the ſpirit made uſe of the tongue to ſpeak forth the praiſe of the Lord; and let <hi>Iohn Auſtine</hi> here obſerve his ignorance of the teachings and work of the ſpirit of God, for the Lord opening the mouth the tongue and lips ſhews forth his praiſe, and God having ſent the ſpiri, of his Son into our hearts, we cry abba, father, and to him return all praiſet</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115594:16"/>
                     <p>But to conclude and be ſhort, obſerve this all you that read it, and take notice of the actings of the Magiſtrates here at <hi>Banbury,</hi> who cauſed <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> to be taken out of the ſtreets, as he were paſſing quietly in them, and put him that night in priſon, and called him the next day before them, where they held their Court, and after ſome diſpute, but the breach of no Law laid to his charge, nor any accuſer were againſt him (but ſuch as ſate to Judge) and no Law mentioned, though deſired, that were tranſgreſſed, and after they had tendred the Oath of Abjuration unto him, who denyed what was in it contained, and all Popiſh wayes, and Jeſuiticall Opinions whatſoever; then the mayor &amp; others ſaid, if that <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> would pay the Sergeant his Fees, and go out of the town that night, he might go free, but if not, he ſhould be re-committed, or ſent to Priſon again; but <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Farnſworth</hi> could not be a friend to deceit, nor pay ſees for a nights falſe impriſonment, taken as he were quietly, with another friend, walking up the ſtreet, and ſo they made a Mittimus and gave to the Goaler, and both before and after he had it given to him, they made a ſpeech, and ſaid, if he would pay his ſees in the Court, he might go free; and when he could not for conſcience ſake towards God then do it; after that one of their party ſaid, Who was ſelf will'd now? to which he (to wit, <hi>R. F.</hi>) anſwered and ſaid, Not he that denyeth to pay ſees for a nights falſe impriſonment, but ſuch as did ſo in their wills, wilfully perſecute and impriſon the ſervants of Jeſus, contrary to Law and Goſpel both, and here it is to be obſerved, that <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi>'s detaining in Priſon, is becauſe he could not be a friend to deceit, and acknowledg a falſe impriſonment, and pay fees for the ſame, being taken out of the high way or ſtreet, as he were paſſing quietly on, and ſent to Priſon; and to colour over their deceit withall, they have added ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall lyes in a Mittimus, and here is kept in priſon for ſtanding faithful to the Lord, and cannot have any fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſs, but rather reprove them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11.</p>
                     <p>And their partiallity is to be obſerved here in this caſe as wel as the reſt, for two were committed to Priſon in <hi>Banbury,</hi> and kept three dayes and three nights, and no fees, as it is ſaid, were demanded of them, but put out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and one out at one end of the town, and another at the other end, and yet though they did ſo, being then, they may be aſhamed of what they had done, but hardning their ſelves againſt the truth, to act wilfully in their wills, they detain one for not paying ſees for one nights impriſonment, for the breach of no Law, then either proved againſt him or laid to his charge.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>VVritten in Banbury</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>the beginning of the 8th. Month, in the Year, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the worlds account,</hi> October <hi>the 7th.</hi> 1655.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="declaration">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115594:17"/>
                  <p>A TRUE DECLARATION OF The Suffering of the Innocent, who is hated and perſecuted without a cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is diſcovered the zeal of the Magiſtrates and people of <hi>Banbury,</hi> perſecuting and impriſoning them that are ſent of the Lord in love to their ſouls, to warm them of the evil of their wayes.</p>
                  <p>Declared in a Letter ſent to <hi>William Allen,</hi> called Juſtice of Peace, with an Anſwer to the falſe accuſations charged upon the INNOCENT.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, their Proceeeings laid open, and proved to bee contrary to the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Anne Audland,</hi> whom the world ſcornfully calls <hi>QUAKER.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Sam. 2.20.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The Adverſaries of the Lord ſhall be broken to pieces: out of heaven ſhall he thunder upon them. The Lord ſhall judge the ends of the earth: and he ſhall give ſtrength unto his King, and exalt the horn of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts 2.18.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And on my ſervants and on my handmaidens, I will poure out in thoſe dayes of my Spirit, and they ſhall propheſie.</p>
                  </q>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <p>
                        <hi>WIlliam Allen,</hi> Juſtice of Peace ſo called, but little peace I finde in thee; We came to the Town of <hi>Banbury</hi> on the thirteenth day of the eleventh moneth, and being ſtrangers, we took in at the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115594:17"/>Lyon: The next day being the firſt day of the week, we went to a meeting which we heard of in the Town; and when the meeting ended, we were moved to go to the Steeplehouſe, to ſpeak the word of the Lord to Prieſt and People; and in obedience to the Lord, we went, and ſtayed till the Prieſt had done, and then my friend ſpoke to the Prieſt, and the rude mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude came and hurried her forth, as the cuſtomes of the Heathens is; Then I ſpoke to the Prieſt, Man, here ſee the fruits of thy Miniſtery, and preſently the rude people hurried me forth: Then came one and took mee by the hand, and queſtioned me, what untruths their Miniſter had ſpoken; and J anſwered, That they that are out of the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all they ſpoke was untruth, And though they ſay, <hi>The Lord liveth,</hi> ſurely they ſwear falſely, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.2.</p>
                     <p>Then another asked me, If the Lord did not live; I anſwered, Yea, <hi>I know he liveth.</hi> Now there are two Boyes that hath ſworn againſt me, that which I did not ſpeak, their blood will be required of them that cauſed them to erre: And know this, O man, that the Lord God wil be avenged of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Juſtices, and he will make his power known in the deſtruction of his Enemies; Therefore fear him, and beware of perſecuting his ſervants, for juſtly ſhalt thou be judged, according to thy deeds done in the body ſhalt thou receive thy reward; To the light in thy conſcience do I direct thee, it will let thee ſee all thy actions, and from whence they ariſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Spirit of Meekneſs, or from thy perverſe will, which the Lord will judge righteouſly; To that in thy conſcience I ſpeak, which will witneſſ for God againſt all deceit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This was I moved to write to clear my conſcience of thee, and leave thee without excuſe, that when the Book of</hi> Conſcience <hi>is opened, thou mayeſt remember that thou waſt warned in thy life-time. A friend of the Truth, and a lover of thy Soul, who is a priſoner of the Lord for the truths ſake at</hi> Banbury, <hi>whoſe name (in the fleſh) is,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Anne Audland.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Anne Audland" type="testimony">
                     <p>WHeereas I am accuſed in a <hi>Mittimus</hi> for certain blaſphemous words, ſaying, <hi>That the Lord liveth not;</hi> I anſwer, theſe words are falſe, and never ſpoken by me: <hi>The Lord is my Redeemer, and I know that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer liveth, and my Soul magnifieth him, and my ſpirit rejoyceth in him;</hi> and here I deny your falſe accuſations and blaſphemy, it is your owne words, and not what I ſaid; and you that accuſe falſely know not the living God, the Heathens knows not God, and the Heathens rage, but the Lord will be avenged of all his Enemies, and plead the cauſe of the innocent: And <hi>they are blaſphemers, which ſay they are</hi> Jews, <hi>and are not, but are the Synagogue of Satan.</hi> And whereas I am accuſed for cauſing a tumult in the Church, when the Miniſter was going to execute part of his Function, and likewiſe to aſſault the Miniſter; I anſwer, This is likewiſe falſe; Lyars muſt bee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115594:18"/>caſt into the lake; The Church is built of living ſtones, elect, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and there is order kept in the Church; And I did not cauſe a tumult neither did I aſſault the Miniſter, (as you call him) and that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led part of his function, is an invention; and there is neither command nor example in all the Scripture, that ever any of the Miniſters of Chriſt did ſprinckle Infants and call it a Function; and here you have no Scripture to prove your Function, as you call it; And he that practiſes ſuch things, for the which there is no Scripture, leads people into the inventions, and ſo they are not profited at all, as it appears by your own words, that they were in a tumult. O bluſh, and be aſhamed of that which you call your Church, who are ſo ſuddenly in a tumult! Was there ever ſuch a thing heard of amongſt the Saints, that they would be in a tumult, when one came in peaceably among them, not offering wrong to any? Here you drew your ſelves to be children of your fathers, who lived in envy, haling out of Synagogues, carrying them before Rulers, and caſting into priſons them who was called of the Lord to bear witneſs againſt their deceit; and here (him called the Miniſter) is made manifeſt to be one that runs before he was ſent, and ſo never profited the people; and ſo like Prieſt, like People. Therefore give over, and never call it a Church, who are fighters and ſtrikers, ſcoffers and ſcorners, tumulters and falſe accuſers, as your fruits makes it daily appear; And ſome of you confeſs, that they are in danger of their lives that comes among you, the people are ſo rude. Now you that are Magiſtrates, ought to puniſh evil Dors, Fighters, and Lyars, and falſe Accuſers; but ſuch have liberty, and dare do it in your Church (as you call it) and you preſent, as hee that cauſed the <hi>Mittimus</hi> to be made doth confeſs, That there was a tumult when hee was preſent, and they that tumulted are not puniſhed, but the fault is laid upon the innocent, who was beat and abuſed, but offered violence to none: And ſo they ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> was a peſtilent fellow, and they tumulted <hi>Paul,</hi> but <hi>Paul</hi> did not cauſe the tumult: So you are made manifeſt of what generation you are, and you ſhall be reworded according to your deeds: And from the Lord I declare, That he will viſit for theſe things, and plead with you for all your hard ſpeeches, and all your ungodly deeds, and give you your portion with hypocrites, except you ſpeedily repent: and when you come into the pit, remember you are warned in your life-time: And ſo your falſe accuſation and blaſphemy I do deny, and the living God will judg between me and you.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>The Burrough of</hi> Banbury <hi>in the county of</hi> Oxon.</dateline>
                        <signed>Anne Audland.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="account">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115594:18"/>
                     <p>THe righteous Judge of all the world is now ariſing, <hi>to judg the world in righteouſneſs, and the people with equity: And every tongue ſhall confeſſe that the Lord is righteous, when be comes to judgement, and he wil reward every one according to that deeds; And every tongue ſhall confeſs the Lord is juſt,</hi> For according to that in the conſcience, which is juſt and equall, will the Lord judg, whoſe <hi>Iudgements</hi> are juſt and equall; and every Tongue ſhall confeſs him juſt, when he takes Vengeance upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt: And behold the Lord commeth with ten thouſands of his Saints to execute Judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches, which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken: And ſuch are they that walk after their own Luſts, and their mouth ſpeaks great ſwelling words, having mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage, ſuch will the Lord execute Judgment upon in righteouſneſs: All you that are ungodly, the Lord will reward you according to your deeds: And all you that utter hard ſpeeches againſt the Holy One, and blaſpheme God in his Temple, The Lord is coming with his Saints to execute Judgment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; and you ſhall confeſs his judgements is juſt, that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth you of your ungodly deeds, and hard ſpeeches, by it you ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Lord is juſt, when you are judged for your ungodly deeds, and hard ſpeeches: And all you that have mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, you ſhall be judged righteouſly, and you ſhall confeſs that God is juſt, and his wayes equall, and God reſpects no mans perſon; nor the Saints who comes with him to Judgment, reſpects no mans perſon; <hi>for he that reſpects perſons commits ſin, and is convinced to be a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of the righteous law of God;</hi> but they who are guided by that which convinceth the tranſgreſſor, they are kept out of the tranſgreſſion, and they do not admire mens perſons, nor reſpect mens perſons. But you that do, are convinced to be tranſgreſſors, and according to that which convinceth, will you be judged by the righteous Judge, who cometh with ten thouſands of his Saints, and he will judge all you that reſpects per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for the Lord regards the rich no more than the poor, but this is hee that the Lord regardeth, who is of an humble and contrite ſpirit, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth at his word: Such you do not regard, who are poor, and trembleth at the word of the Lord: but you that reſpects perſons, ſcoffs at ſuch as they go along the ſtreets: <hi>But the Lord will plead the cauſe of the poore, who is now despiſed amongſt you that reſpects perſons: You admire ſome mens Perſons becauſe of advantage, and ye despiſe others, and Perſecutes the Poore, and goes about to make one an offender for a word, which is none indeed; and you ſet a ſnare for them that reprove in the Gate, that ſo you might catch the innocent, and they that are offenders indeed, who can lye, and ſweare and accuſe falſely, ſuch have liberty, and ſuch are ſet to enſnare the innocent, and to be as Iudges againſt the innocent, and yet you profeſs your ſelves Chriſtians.</hi> Oh that you were wiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh that you would conſider your latter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115594:19"/>end! How will you ſtand before the Judgment ſeat of God, in the day when the ſecrets of every heart ſhall be judged by Jeſus Chriſt, who hath all judgement committed to him: And behold he cometh, and all the Saints with him, and he rules and reigns in his Saints, and ſits upon his Throne: But how will you ſtand at that day, who now ſits as judges upon the Saints, and calls them deceivers, and perſecutes them, who are made free by the Son of God, and in obedience to him ſuffers the loſs of all things, and are kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the day long, and are accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter; and are become a reproach, and a by-word, and a ſcorn, even among you that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves Chriſtians, and ſo the Scripture is fulfilled, They that work wickedneſs are ſet up, and they that departs from iniquity becomes a prey to the wicked, and the Sufferings of the Saints is become a ſport amongſt you; and you can ſtretch your ſelves upon your beds of eaſe; and you do not remember the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> nor you have not known, that all who live godly in Chriſt Jeſus muſt ſuffer perſecution; and ſaith Chriſt, <hi>As they have done unto me, ſo will they do unto you: And the Servant is not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now if you were Chriſtians, as you profeſs your ſelves to be, then would perſecution ceaſe and not be found amongſt you; for Chriſtians doth not perſecute, but you that live in ſuch things, are made manifeſt, (to all the children of Light) whoſe ſervants you are; and you that are Magiſtrates who ſhould puniſh evil Doers, ſuch have liberty in the Streets to ſcoffe and ſcorn, to ſwear and lie, and be drunk, and you paſs by theſe things; but if any come amongſt you to declare the word of the Lord againſt ſuch things then the innocent are accuſed by them who live in ſuch things, and the innocent are perſecuted and ſent to priſon, and may not know from you who priſons them, what they are accuſed of, nor ſee their accuſers face to face; Is this according to the Law of God? or is this as you would be done unto? Conſider of it, and lay it to heart, <hi>for the Lord wil viſit for theſe things,</hi> I ſpeak what I know, and find amongſt you; for I was accuſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Priſon, but I did not know what the accuſers ſwore againſt me, neither could I ſee my accuſers; but you took an oath in ſecret, and ſo I was accuſed and committed for that which I never ſpoke, and had not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to anſwer for my ſelf, nor others had no liberty nor could be heard on my behalf, who was by when (they ſay) I ſpoke theſe words, for which I am accuſed, which would bear teſtimony, that they heard no ſuch things ſpoken by me, as I am accuſed of, and ſo the innocent ſuffers innocently; and in the mean time wickedneſs is at liberty, and not onely in a corner, but in your ſtreets; men lie, and ſwear, and are drunk, and the innocent is a prey unto them; and yet you do not lay it to heart; woe is me for you, that you ſhould ſo ſlight the day of your viſiitation, and ſo wickedly requite the Lord for all his goodneſs, as to perſecute his ſervants, who are ſent to warn you; and deſpiſe his Witneſſes, and ſhamefully intreat his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and them that comes to you in their owne names ſuch you receive;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115594:19"/>but them that come to you in the name of the Lord, ſuch are a reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you; and the Lord is highly diſpleaſed with you for theſe things; and he wil make enquiry for blood; you know that the blood of the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent hath been ſhed in your Streets; one that came amongſt you, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered violence to none, was beat and abuſed, and loſt much blood amongſt you, and yet you are not aſhamed to profeſs your ſelves Chriſtians, when as theſe actions proceeds from you; and your care is how to wound the innocent ſecretly, that ſo your deeds might not be brought to the light; but it is in vain for you to dig deep to hide your counſel from the Lord; <hi>VVoe unto you that deviſeth to work miſchief in the dark, and ſay, who ſeeth us? and conſults together to ſhoot your arrowes ſecretly againſt the poor.</hi> The Lord ſees you, &amp; knows your hearts, &amp; your very thoughts which you think againſt the King in your bed-chamber; there is a bird of the ayre that carries the voyce; And <hi>the Lord will bring every work to judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or evill;</hi> and the oath in ſecret ſhall be tryed; and the Lord wil ſit as Judge amongſt the Judges; and you ſhall all be weighed and thoſe of you that are found wanting, the Lord will caſt you by, though you be as high and mighty as <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> was; and if you be angry with mee for telling you ſo, and forewarning you in your life-time; the Lord will judge you for it; for he is tender over his little ones; and in as much as you perſecute one of them, ye do it unto him; and you that impriſon the innocent, and they may not ſee their accuſers; is this according to the Law of God? or, is this to judge for God, and not for man, nor ſelf-ends without reſpect of perſons? They that were ſet over the <hi>people</hi> to judge them according to the Law of God, <hi>were juſt men fearing God, and hating covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> juſt men were to judge the unjuſt; for the unjuſt cannot judge true judgment: See what charge <hi>Ichoſhaphat</hi> gave unto them he ſet over the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6, 7, 9, <hi>Saying to the Iudges, take heed what you do, for you judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the judgement: wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, and take heed and do it, for there is no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts: And he charged them ſaying, thus ſhall ye do in the fear of the</hi> Lord <hi>faithfully, and with a perfect heart:</hi> Now all you that denies a perfect heart, and are reſpecters of perſons, you cannot judge with a perfect heart; and ſuch are not Judges for God, who judges not with a perfect heart; but are reſpecters of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but they who fear God, and do faithfully with a perfect heart, ſuch Judges and Magiſtrates I own who are juſt men; ſuch rules for God, and is a terror to the wicked, and for the praiſe of them that do well; and ſuch I am ſubject to for conſcience-ſake; but they who were the ſervants of Chriſt &amp; miniſters of Chriſt, when they were commanded by the rulers that which was contrary to the command of Chriſt, they ſaid, whether is it better to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God, or Man, judg ye; and I ſay the ſame, and they which command any thing contrary to the command of Chriſt, which rules and reigns in his <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> &amp; is one in the <hi>male</hi> and in the <hi>female;</hi> ſuch are not juſt men fearing God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115594:20"/>and judging faithfully with a perfect heart; and ſuch who do not fear God and have not a perfect heart, ſuch knowes not the voyce of God; but Chriſts ſheep who follow Chriſt, and are ſent of God knows his voyce: Now Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and People will ſay, how may we know that you are ſent of God? as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid to <hi>Moſes, VVho ſent thee?</hi> and he anſwered, <hi>The Lord ſent me, to bid thee let Iſrael go free;</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, <hi>I know not the Lord, neither will I obey him, and let Iſrael go free;</hi> Such are they who fear not God nor know not his voice; and ſuch cannot diſcern the things of God, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates nor People, who fear not God, and have not a perfect heart: Now conſider if you judg me according to the Law of God, when you heard all that was againſt me, and did accuſe me, but would not hear the accuſed, and the accuſers face to face, nor thoſe that was by, who would have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt thoſe untruths charged upon me, but put them forth and ſaid, What have you to do here? notwithſtanding, they ſaid they came to bear witneſs to the truth: See how <hi>Moſes</hi> charged the Judges, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16.17. ſaying, <hi>Hear the cauſe between your brethren, and judge righteouſly between every man and his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him; ye ſhall not reſpect perſons in judgment, but you ſhall hear the ſmall as well as the great; ye ſhall not be afraid if the face of man; for the judgment is Gods:</hi> and Deut. 19.16,18, 20. <hi>The Iudges and Officers was to judge the people with juſt judgment; thou ſhalt not wreſt judgment; thou ſtall not reſpect perſons; neither take a gift, for a gift doth blinde the eye of the wiſe, and perverts the words of the righteous; that which is altogether juſt ſhall thou follow, that thou mayeſt live and inherit the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee:</hi> Now this is true judgment, and takes hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the unjuſt; but here you do not act according to the Law of God, who doth reſpect perſons, and doth not hear the ſmall as wel as the great, which you have not done who have committed me to priſon, and I had not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſpeak face to face with my accuſers, and ſo I am falſly accuſed and impriſoned upon a falſe accuſation, he that knows all ſecrets is my witneſs; and he will plead my cauſe, and he will judge righteous judgment upon all the Heathen; and the Lord comes with his Saints; and this honour have all the Saints, to execute upon the Heathen all the judgements written; but the Heathen ought not to judg the Saints; but the Heathen rages, &amp; the heathen perſecutes and impriſons, &amp; falſly accuſeth the Saints, &amp; the viols of wrath is now to be poured out upon the wicked; and the Saints ſhall take the kingdom &amp; rejoyce in God for ever &amp; ever, which giveth them victory over the world, and gives them ſtrength to rejoyce in tribulation; Prayſes to the living God for evermore. And ſo I warn you all People, Magiſtrates, and Teachers, to fear the Lord God, leſt his wrath and indignation break forth againſt you, and the decree be ſealed, and he take you away with his grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſtroke, and there be no remedy; for God is my witneſs, that my deſire is for you, that you may know the things that belongs to your peace; ſo to you all I have cleared my conſcience, and I am free from your blood, glory to the Lord for evermore, who hath given me to believe and ſuffer for the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115594:20"/>of Jeſus; ſo I remain a witneſs for the truth, &amp; a priſoner in bonds at <hi>Banbury,</hi> for the truths ſake, who am innocent, but falſly accuſed &amp; ſlandered &amp; reproached; but the reproaches for Chriſt is my riches, whoſe name in the fleſh is,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Anne Audland.</signed>
                        <date>The 5 day of the 12 month. 1654</date>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>To you Magiſtrates of the Town of <hi>Banbury,</hi> and to thee <hi>John Griffith,</hi> who was called Deputy-Recorder, &amp; ſate <hi>Iudg</hi> in the Seſsions (or pretended Goal-Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very) holden the <hi>26</hi> day of the <hi>7</hi> moneth, <hi>1655.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is likely, the heat of pour paſſions being over, you may ſince (in the cool of the day) better have conſidered your actions don that day in your court, which if with the light of Chriſt Jeſus you have,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8.</note> it wil ſhew you that thoſe who reſpect the perſon of any man, commits ſin, &amp; are found tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the pure &amp; righteous law of God, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.1, 9. which ſaith, <hi>thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honor the perſon of the mighty; but in righteouſnes ſhalt thou judg thy neighbor, Lev.</hi> 19.15. which if you hearken to, and regard the Law written in the heart, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. it will reprove you for your partial act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that day, and tell you, that you did not do wel to fine <hi>Thomas Cole</hi> five pounds, and for to impriſon him till he ſhould pay the ſame, (and to bee angry with him) for keeping on his hat in your Court, and afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite two other men for to put on their hats in your Court, (namely Prieſt <hi>Jones</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Smart;</hi>) conſider, if this were not partiality, and to reſpect perſons, and for to act contrary to equity and truth, as that in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wil let you ſee, and with mee bear a true teſtimonie; And whether your ſending of <hi>Jane VVaugh, Sarah Tyms</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel VVeſton</hi> to priſon again, (they neither convinced of, nor being charged with the breach of any known Law, nor ſo much as one witneſs proving them guilty of the leaſt miſdemeanor,) were not injuſtice yea, or no; And whether if you had ſet them free (ſeeing there was nothing laid to their charge) you had not done juſtly, and according to Law, Equity, and good conſcience, (what the Law of the Land requireth) and what you are ſworn to do, yea or no; If ſo, conſider then, and let mee know what Law I have tranſgreſſed, and wherefore you have committed me to priſon; which thing if then you had done, I ſhould not now need to have required of you; ſo if with the true Light of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> wherewithall you are enlightned, (which light opens the blind eye) you weigh and duly conſider your actions that day, you will ſee they were not wrought in God,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19, <hi>&amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </note> but proceeded from that ground and tree which God hath curſed, and brings forth the ſame evil fruit which the chief Prieſts and Elders did that crucified CHRIST JESUS, and hath perſecuted the Saints in all ages, as may be ſeen in the writings of the Apoſtles, (and in the Hiſtories of the Books of Martyrs) which light of Chriſt Jeſus if you love, (and bring your deeds to it) it wil cauſe you to repent, and to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115594:21"/>forſake your evill deeds,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24— <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.35. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.23. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8. <hi>Mal.</hi> 25.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29, 30. <hi>Rom</hi> 1.28.</note> and for to teſtifie againſt the like evil wayes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it will lead you in a new way, which is called Holy, and will crucifie and change your nature (that was accuſtomed to ſin,) 'twill bring you to the New Birth, and the New Man, you wil know which is treated in Chriſt Ieſus to walk in good works, which New Man will love God, and do his will, and work righteouſneſs, ſuch as he therein accepteth; and all this by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will he work in all them that believe and follow him, who is the Light of the world, and this is the meaſure of light that comes from him, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves you of ſin, and is your Talent which God hath given you, which Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent (or meaſure of Light) if you improve not, but hide it under your earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minds, (cover it under the love of the World, as pleaſures, profits, and reſpects and honours from man, and love theſe things more than it) you hate Chriſt, who rejects his light, and are the unprofitable ſervant, whoſe Talent will be taken away, and you caſt into darkneſs, and there you are in the tranſgreſſion, in the fall, in the old man, in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi>'s nature, which is the firſt breach which God hates,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8, 7, 8.</note> and his curſe is to, and his wrath abides upon, which nature can never pleaſe God, but is the envious nature that ſlew <hi>Abell,</hi> releaſed <hi>Barrabas,</hi> and crucified Chriſt Ieſus; and as it was then, ſo it is now, they that are after the fleſh, and abide in that nature, which is turned from the Light, perſecute them that are (guided by the Light into the new life, and walk) after the ſpirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. And they in the firſt nature (turned from the <hi>Light</hi>) <hi>although they have eyes, yet ſee not; have ears;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.40.</note> 
                        <hi>but hear not, and have a heart, but cannot contain aright of the things of God,</hi> therefore they in it, <hi>call evill good, and good evill;</hi> And although thoſe that be in this firſt nature talk of the things of God,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> 
                        <hi>and saih the Lord lives, yet ſurely do they ſwear falſely, Ier.</hi> 5.2. (although he lives for ever) for the life of God was ever hid from that nature; and although they who live in that firſt nature (that obey not the Light) pray or perform any other duty, which God had commanded, <hi>yet it is an abomination to him; whoſe ear is turned from the Law, by the light written in the heart, Pro.</hi> 28.9. And as in the Scriptures may be read,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8.</note> 
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. <hi>They who chooſe their own way, that delighteth in abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if they kil an Ox, it is as if they slew a Man; if they ſacrifice a lamb, as if they cut off a dogs neck; if they offer an oblation, as if thy offered Swines blood:</hi> So you and your Prieſts, who are ſtill in the old nature, in the works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which hate the Light, and know not the new birth, as your fruits makes manifeſt, may ſee what your preachings and prayers, faſting, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will avail you,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</note> while you live in envy and perſecution, in pride and love of the world, they (are <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice, not accepted, and) will ſtand you but in little ſtead, no more than they did your forefathers, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> who talked of the Scriptures, and knew many things outwardly from them, and ſpoke of a Saviour that was to come, and made their brags of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Moſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.39. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31.</note> of the Law and the Prophets, and could cry Lord, Lord, and drew neer him with their lips, when their hearts were awhoring after their covetouſneſs, pride, love of the world, and praiſe of men; and while they were
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115594:21"/>crying up the Temple, and outward Ordinances of God,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17.</note> they crucified Chriſt Jeſus who was the end, or ſubſtance, of the Law and the Prophets, and of all thoſe outward Types and Figures, as you do now, who talk of the Scriptures, and of faith and love in Chriſt Jeſus, whenas you hate his light, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them that follow it, and with it are led out of the worlds wayes, faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and traditions, into the life and practiſe of thoſe which writ the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.15, 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14.15. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9, 10.</note> who were not of this world, but were choſen out of it, to teſtifie againſt it that the works thereof are evill; ſo whileſt your bodies are the Synagogue of Satan, and by him you are acted into envy and perſecution, and do not thoſe things which Chriſt Jeſus calls for, by his pure light in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, all your talk and profeſſion (being in the nature hating and turned from the light) is in vain, and you ſtill remain in your ſine: therefore to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus (which makes the tree good, that makes the fruit good) I direct you, which Light, if you love, believe in, and follow, it will reach you to deny all ungodlineſs, worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.33, 34, 35. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.27. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.10.</note> and righteouſly in this preſent world, to be meek, and to be humble, and to do unto all as you would be done unto; ſo in love to your ſouls have I writ this, that with the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your conſciences (which ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the heart and tryeth the Reins) you may ſee your ſelves, and what it is that guides you, and whoſe ſervants you are, and from what root and ground (the off-ſpring) your words, actions, and thoughts do proceed, there being only two roots, from whence all words, actions and thoughts do come, good and evil, &amp; his ſervants you are to whom you yeild obedience, whether of ſin unto death, or of obedience unto righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. Therefore friends and people, be not deceived with a vain talk,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.35. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16.</note> and an outſide proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, your lives being contrary, and (ye cannot ſerve two Maſters) God wil be no longer mocked by you, <hi>for ſuch as you ſo ſowe, ſuch ſhall you reap, and what meaſure you meet, ſhall be meaſured to you again, wel heapped, preſſed down,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7, 8,</note> 
                        <hi>and running over;</hi> wherefore while you have time priſe it, and reject not the day of Gods viſitation, neither harden your hearts againſt him, as he calleth you to repentance, and ſo you continue in your evil practiſes,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7, 8.</note> and you be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by his juſt hand. And now ſeeing the Lord God is riſen in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to teſtifie againſt your evill wayes: beware you are not found fighters againſt him, he wil be too hard for you to kick againſt. So I have cleared my conſcience unto you,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iude</hi> 14.17.</note> and remember that in your life time you have bin warned; By a Servant of the Lord, known by the name of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Robert Rich.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115594:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A</hi> Copie of a Letter ſent from <hi>Thomas Curtis,</hi> who had been a Captain in the Parliaments Army, to <hi>Samuell VVells,</hi> profeſſed Miniſter of the Town of <hi>Banbury,</hi> and ſent to him into the Court or Seſſions, then holden in <hi>Banbury,</hi> the 27. day of the 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Month, 1655.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Am not a ſtranger to thy former converſation, and now am witneſs of thy unjuſt actions, thy deeds make manifeſt of what <hi>Generation</hi> thou art, and on what foundation thou ſtandeſt. Call to mind thy former <hi>Prayers,</hi> when we were in the Army, driven from our Homes, perſecuted by <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> put to fight for our <hi>Freedoms</hi> and our <hi>Religion,</hi> as then thou told'ſt us of; is it all come to this? Haſt thou forgotten thy <hi>Vowes, Proteſtations</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> then made in thy <hi>Prayers, How that if God would deliver us, how we would walk in newneſs of life,</hi> and now the Lord hath delivered, <hi>How art thou turned perſecutor if the righteous ſeed of God?</hi> Call to mind how thou wouldſt cry out againſt <hi>Parents</hi> that did not breed up their <hi>Children</hi> in <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>ſoberneſs:</hi> Now thou haſt gotten a great living, and no place that ever I came in (as I can remember) ſo vile as this Town (of <hi>Banbury</hi>) under thy teaching; Oh ſee the <hi>fruits</hi> of thy <hi>miniſtry! children ſcoffing, haling, ſtoning, and evill ſpeaking, and their Parents looking on, and countenancing them, laughing at them ſo doing:</hi> it is a ſad ſight to ſee ſuch a <hi>reformation, and will not the Lord viſit for theſe things?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9.</note> what may we look at, but that it is <hi>like people like prieſt?</hi> Call to mind thy perſecuting of the <hi>innocent,</hi> and cauſing the <hi>Peace</hi> to be broken by thy own ſelf, and caſting it on the innocent, making them to ſuffer for it; <hi>Canſt thou behold theſe things and not bluſh? How durſt thou call thy ſelfe a miniſter of Chriſt and perſecute? VVas ever any of the true Prophets, Apoſtles, or Ieſus Chriſt a perſecutor? Did ever they, when one came into their meeting, and ſtand ſilent there, call to the magiſtrate to take him away, and out him in priſon, and ſay they could not go on in their prayer, and then after a long impriſonment, ſee him arraigned at the Bar for breaking the peace, whenas thou was the cauſe?</hi> Was it not thy ſelfe that cauſed the people to be breakers of the peace, and then make the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſuffer for it? Is this according to Scripture? Did the Lord ſend his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115594:22"/>to cry againſt them that made men <hi>offenders</hi> for a word, &amp; ſet ſnares for them that reproved in the Gate? <hi>And canſt thou eſcape, who makeſt a man an offender before he ſpake a word? The juſt God wil ſurely finde thee out &amp; al Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; for wo to them ſaith the Lord God, that hath cauſed my people to err, &amp; daub with untempred Morter, and cry peace to them to whom God hath not ſpoken peace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Ezek</hi> 13.10.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſo ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked;</hi> juſt as it was with the falſe Prophets ſo is it now, <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſe things, the Prieſts bear rule by their means, and the people love to have it ſo.</hi> But read thy portion; what wilt thou do in the end thereof? See again thy ſubtill dealing with <hi>Anne Audland,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.27, 28, 29, 30, 31.</note> that when all the perſecution that wit could invent to take away her life for <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> would not reach, but ſhe was acquitted by the Jury: There muſt be brought her calling the falſe Prophet, and this muſt be called ſcandall, when by the Scripture it is ſoon proved, and to thy ſhame, remember I know thee Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: How often haſt thou ſate night after night at Cards, and ſometimes whole nights playing (and ſometimes compelling me to play with thee) for mony, then waſt thou called of the world a Miniſter, and now art thou turned perſecutor? in the cloſe, ſee thy unjuſt dealing, when thou haſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what the uttermoſt will of man can do, then thou in thy deceit putteſt off thy hat, and deſireſt that ſhe may have as much favour as the Law wil afford her (thou art content to commit thy cauſe to God:) Oh cruel deceit to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver withall! But thy covering is too narrow, it wil not hide thee. Friend, to the pure Light of God in thy conſcience do I ſpeak, and that witneſs in thee knows theſe things to be true, and that an account thou muſt give to the great God of all theſe things; in love to thee do I write, that thou maiſt be warned and repentance witneſs, leſt the indignation of the Lord be poured out upon thee: I have not much more to ſay at preſent, but deſire the Lord that he will open thine eyes, that thou maiſt ſee the evill of thy heart and live; which is the deſire of him, how ever thou eſteemeſt, is a lover of thy eternall peace, and one that ſuffers with the righteous ſeed, called of the World,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>The 27th. day of the 7th. Month 1655.</date>
                     <signed>Tho. Curtis.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="certificate">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115594:23"/>
                  <head>A Certificate of the endeavours or certain Friends which went to the Magiſtrates of <hi>Banbury,</hi> to have had Copies of the Cauſes of the Priſoners Commitment at their late Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and pretended Goale-Delivery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVE, whoſe names are hereunto ſubſcribed, do hereby declare to all unto whom this Preſents ſhal come, that there being a Seſſions (&amp; pretended <hi>Goal-Delivery</hi>) appointed to be holden for the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough of <hi>Banbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxon,</hi> upon the 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> day of the 7th. month 1655. Within which <hi>Burrough,</hi> ſeverall ſervants of the moſt <hi>High God,</hi> whom the world in ſcorn call <hi>Quakers,</hi> were impriſoned, and at the ſame <hi>Seſſions</hi> to be brought to <hi>tryall;</hi> We repaired to the ſaid Town of <hi>Banbury,</hi> and went un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tymothy Harris,</hi> the <hi>Town</hi> Clerk thereof, and in a civill manner deſired <hi>Copyes</hi> of the cauſes of their <hi>Commitments,</hi> who abſolutely denyed to give any; whereupon we went to <hi>Iohn Griffith</hi> Deputy-Recorder, the Mayor, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers celled Juſtices of the ſaid <hi>Burrough,</hi> who were all met together at the Mayors houſe, and deſired of them that we might have <hi>Copies</hi> of their ſaid <hi>commitments,</hi> whereupon they adviſed us to repair to the <hi>Town-Clerk</hi> for the ſame; and they being informed that he had denyed it, ſaid we might demand it in Court; whereupon we repaired to their Court, and when their Court was about to be adjourned one of us deſired, that if any Bills of Indictment were there preferred againſt the aforeſaid <hi>friends,</hi> and particularly againſt <hi>Anne Audland,</hi> he might have <hi>Copies</hi> thereof; and the ſaid <hi>Deputy-Recorder</hi> ſaid he ſhould have it, but going to the <hi>Town-Clerk</hi> for the ſame, he refuſed it, and the <hi>Deputy-Recorder</hi> being informed thereof, took no courſe that we might have it; in the afternoon <hi>Robert Rich, Nathaniell VVeſton, Anne Aud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Iane VVaugh,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Tims,</hi> were by the ſaid Court (for ought ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to us, then preſent in the Court) committed to priſon, no breach of the Law being charged upon them, whereupon the next day we went to the <hi>Deputy-Recorder</hi> again, after the <hi>Seſſions</hi> was ended, and deſired of him that we might have <hi>copyes</hi> of the cauſes of the <hi>commitments</hi> of the perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, who ſaid he <hi>was but a Deputy-Recorder, and had no power to do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therein, the Seſſions being ended,</hi> but adviſed us <hi>to repaire to the</hi> Mayor <hi>and</hi> Town-Clerk <hi>for the ſame;</hi> whereupon we went to the <hi>Town-Clerk,</hi> and one of us informed him that the <hi>perſons</hi> aforeſaid being committed in Court, he conceived the <hi>cauſes</hi> of their <hi>commitments</hi> were <hi>entred</hi> upon <hi>record,</hi> and therefore deſired <hi>copyes</hi> thereof: who abſolutely denyed the ſame, ſaying, <hi>we lacked ſomething to be prating, and ſaid that they were committed til they did finde ſureties for their good-behaviour, and there they ſhou'd ſtay until they had ſo done,</hi> or words to the ſame <hi>effects.</hi> In teſtimony whereof we have hereunto ſet our Hands,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Gouldney, Thomas Curtis, Edward Pyat, VValter Clement.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="considerations">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115594:23"/>
                  <head>Some CONSIDERATIONS upon the Proceedings againſt the PRISONERS, or the Innocent ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers for the Teſtimony of JESUS in Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, at the late Aſſize, Seſſions, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Goal-Delivery.</head>
                  <p>NOw all you that deſire to fear God, and ſuch as do fear God, theſe things are left to your conſiderations (as wel as the actors againſt the innocent,) conſider of theſe things and lay them to heart, for by this may appear the cruel perſecution of the innocent at <hi>Banbury;</hi> firſt, one <hi>Anne Audland</hi> that were impriſoned upon a pretence of Blaſphemy, (though not found) and after long impriſonment or bonds, appeared at the Aſſizes or Seſſions, and a Jury called (of life and death) and the ſufferer called to the Bar, and could not by any means (though endeavours were uſed) have a Copy of what was preferred againſt her (though in danger of life;) was not this as much as in them lay to bind her from anſwering for her ſelf, and for making her defence againſt her adverſaries? And was not this to make them guilty of the blood of the innocent, if the Lord had not preſerved from the wrath and violence of unreaſonable men? Oh the ſubtilty and cruelty of the enemies of the children of God! Was it ever known that the like (amongſt thoſe that bear the name of Chriſtians, or reaſonable men) were ever ſo acted before? And was it not a great crime, or high miſdemeanour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, for (one called) a Magiſtrate, who had ſate on the bench, to go amongſt the Jury of life and death, and to endeavour to corrupt and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate them? After their ends about blaſphemy were fruſtrated, who could not find the Bill for blaſphemy againſt the Priſoner, but threw it by, not having Evidence to prove it: Did not he labour againſt the truth, leſt the innocencie of the Priſoner ſhould have been cleared? And was it not to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Priſoner from being by due courſe of law freed? Was their actings therein either according to equity, reaſon, or juſtice? Conſider wel of it: And are you offended to be told of your unreaſonable or unjuſt proceedings againſt the innocent? And although the Bill againſt the priſoner was laid for blaſphemy, yet blaſphemy was not found (by the Jury;) but to colour over deceit withall: Was not a lye added in ſaying ſhe was ſcandalous, for calling the Miniſter a falſe Prophet (when ſhe did not) and ſo re-commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her to priſon again for that? Was not that contrary to Law, Equity, and Reaſon? Let all reaſonable men and ſuch as know the Law of God, and obey the ſame, herein be Judge; Is there any Law of God that ſaith it is ſcandalous to call a falſe Prophet by the name of a falſe Prophet, and for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115594:24"/>ſo doing commit them to priſon? If ſo, Might not all the true <hi>Prophets</hi> have been <hi>Priſoners</hi> by it? and if there be no Law of God that doth ſo, is there any Law of the Nation contrary to the <hi>Law</hi> of God in that reſpect that doth it? and if not, whether have not theſe men that committed one for ſaying, as they ſay, ſhe called the man a falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> when the did not, although he may eaſily be proved one, and made that a cover to hide themſelves under, when their ends about <hi>blaſphemy</hi> were fruſtrated. Have not they committed a double offence, and acted contrary to the Law of God and the Law of the Land in ſo doing?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3:9.</note> Was this at all either to honour true Iuſtice, or ſet up a Court of true Equity, and do as you would be done by? Or is it not to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your malice and cruelty to all that behold your proceedings, and to lay open the fruits of your Miniſtry and ſpirits to appear one with them that ſay they are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and are not, as they that ſaid they were <hi>Iews</hi> and were not, for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are aſhamed of ſuch <hi>Fruits,</hi> and they never ſo acted, that the <hi>Scripture</hi> relateth; nay, <hi>Doth not your actions herein exceed the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens? VVould not they act according to Law? and do not you act clear contrary?</hi> For one had been <hi>impriſoned</hi> for ſtanding quietly in the <hi>Steeplehouſe</hi> till the <hi>Prieſt</hi> called to take him away, for whil'ſt he ſtood there he could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>pray,</hi> though he ſpake not a word till he were taken away, and when he were after long <hi>impriſonment arraigned</hi> at the <hi>Barre,</hi> never a <hi>witneſs</hi> nor <hi>proſecutor</hi> came againſt him, not any <hi>breach</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> laid to his charge; yet notwithſtanding he might be <hi>re-committed</hi> to <hi>ward</hi> or <hi>Priſon</hi> again, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he would find ſureties for <hi>good-behaviour,</hi> (and if it be <hi>evill-behaviour</hi> to go ſtand in a <hi>ſteeplehouſe</hi> to hear a <hi>Priest,</hi> and ſay nothing till the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſpoke firſt unto them, they would make many in <hi>England</hi> to be in the miſ-behaviour: From hence obſerve and ſee if that which they call <hi>miſ-behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> be not to go hear the Prieſt and ſay nothing, till the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſpeak firſt, according to that account;) but no <hi>miſ-behaviour</hi> was <hi>proved</hi> againſt him, nor the Law tranſgreſſed in any one point, neither did any appear to <hi>proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> any thing againſt him, nor to lay any thing to his charge, yet he might be <hi>re-committed</hi> to <hi>VVard or Priſon</hi> again, and if that be not contrary, both to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> what is? Conſider of it: <hi>And was it not unreaſonable and contrary to Law, to commit to Priſon, and after long impriſonment, being called to the Bar, and then to demand ſureties for good-beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and no miſdemeanour proved, nor any one came againſt the priſoner, either to accuſe or proſecute; Ought not that to have been according to Law, before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was or ought to be demanded. And was it not an unjuſt thing to commit to priſon again for the ſame, when no breach of law was proved againſt the priſoner, neither at his firſt commitment, nor after long impriſonment, when he were arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or called to the Barr:</hi> Is theſe actings either according to Scripture, Law, Equity, or Reaſon? Are you not beſide Scripture, Law, Equity and reaſon (as wel as true Juſtice) herein; or do not ſuch as ſo act, bear the <hi>Sword</hi> in vain? the Lord help you to conſider of it, that you may learn wiſdome (that the heathen may not laugh you to ſcorn:) Ought not the <hi>Priſoner</hi> by law
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115594:24"/>have been acquitted in the Court after long impriſonment, when none came either to accuſe or proſecute againſt him there? and likewiſe <hi>Iane VVaugh,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Tims,</hi> who had been long impriſoned, and called to the Bar, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accuſer came againſt them there, nor one proſecutor, and yet they muſt be re-committed to priſon again, except they would finde ſureties to be of good-behaviour, when none appeared againſt them to accuſe them, or prove againſt them any miſ-behaviour, and neither any breach of Law ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proved againſt them or laid to their charge: is theſe actings either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, Juſtice, Law, Equity, or Reaſon; are they not beſide all theſe in their actings herein? and can they be ſaid to be reaſonable men that ſo act againſt the innocent ſufferers and ſervants of Jeſus, as they at <hi>Banbuoy</hi> have done; conſider wel of it, (and keep paſſion and malice down) and the Lord deliver me, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> from unreaſonable men;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 25.27. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> and it is a true ſaying of the Prophet, the righteous ſuffer, and no man (in his unrighteous nature) layeth it to heart, yet bleſſed are they, as Chriſt hath ſaid, that ſuffers for righteouſneſs ſake, for the Lord Jeſus doth take their parts, and ſo the ſpirit of grace and glory reſteth upon them, as is written and witneſſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 13, 14. Now conſider if all theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and innocent ſufferers would not have been freed by dew courſe of Law, if it had been executed aright, and if any had tranſgreſſed the Law, ought not they then to have been proceeded againſt according to Law, and ſo have had the puniſhment inflicted according to the tranſgreſſion, and have been acquitted; or if no Law could be proved againſt them that they had tranſgreſſed, ought not by Law their accuſers, inſtead of them, to have had the puniſhment which they ſhould have had upon them inflicted, and they by the Law releaſed or remedied: Do you know what uſe the Law is of, or how to act according to it; have you done what you did out of malice or ignorance; conſider of it, and lay theſe things to heart, for be ſure the Lord wil call you to an account for your proceedings againſt the <hi>innocent,</hi> as wel as for all your evill deeds, and then what <hi>account</hi> wil you give, and how will you anſwer before his Judgement ſeat: And withall conſider of this; Was (or is) there any Law, either of <hi>God</hi> or the <hi>Nation,</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth a man to put off his Hat, and if he do not, to fine him <hi>five pounds,</hi> and <hi>commit</hi> him to <hi>priſon</hi> till he pay the ſame (as one <hi>Thomas Cole</hi> an inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant in <hi>Banbuoy</hi> was;) and was it not partiall and contrary to Law, if it had been ſo, for to fine and impriſon one for the ſame, and perſwade other two to the like even in the Court to put on their hats; was not here both partiality and malice made manifeſt, and is not that contrary to the Law of God, and a contempt to the higher power and Authority,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.1. &amp; 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.24, 25, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> which forbids ſuch things, but be ſure you wil nor go unpuniſhed of him, who bears not the ſword in vain, for thus ſaith the Lord (by his ſervant the Prophet) Oh! I will eaſe me of my adverſaries, and avenge me of my enemies, and reſtore Judges as at the firſt, and <hi>counſells</hi> as at the beginning, when no ſuch things were by them neither acted nor done, which can be anywhere
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115594:25"/>proved by Scriptures, which ſtands a witneſs againſt them that profeſs God in words, but in works deny him, as it is written and witneſſed, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. Likewiſe when one <hi>Robert Rich</hi> was moved of the Lord to ſpeak ſomething unto you about the proceedings in your Court, did not you that ſate as jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bid him come up and ſpeak, and preſently changed your minds, or elſe your words, crying out; Pul him down and have him to Priſon, before eyer he had ſaid to you what he had to ſpeak; was that according either to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, truth, equity; or reaſon; could heathens have done any more? Or would not reaſonable men have regarden their word? The Lord ſet theſe things home to your hearts, that you may a little better conſider and lament (as wel as repent) leaſt the evil day come upon you al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> unawares: Did not you at Banbury pretend a Goal-Delivery that day (the Priſoners were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,) but did you intend any ſuch thing; do not your proceedings declare the contrary, and doth not the witneſs of God in your conſciences witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you for it, as wel as your actions: Was not the ſervants of Jeſus that were called before you at the Bar, the greateſt cauſe at your ſize or Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions held in Banbury that day; and was there any Law proved againſt them which they had in any one point tranſgreſſed or broke; or had they procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings according to Law; and was there one of than freed by you, nay, but more added to them, and afterward one taken out or the highway, or ſtreet, and haled to priſon, and no breach of Law laid to his charge, though it were deſired, and alſo the Fact as wel as the Law, by vertue whereof it became a crime, yet it were denyed, and they kept cloſe under the Earth, ſhut up in a hole or dungeon in Banbury, as if they were ſome great Malefactors, and no Law yet laid to their charge that hath been either broken or tranſgreſſed by them; but ſuch as are friends to Chriſtianity and Equity, Truth and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and all ſuch as truly fears God, will conſider of the ſufferings of the Innocent, and lay theſe things to heart, though the wicked, and ſuch as are without the fear of God, regard it not.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
